<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Church of Rome unmask'd, or her false principles briefly detected with some reasons of so many retaining or returning to communion with her, and the great danger of everlasting destruction, that such persons, especially after separations from her, return to her communion, do run themselves on / written by a learned divine, by way of letter to a friend in the country.</title>
            <author>Learned divine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18501</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11747582</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11747582</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33078)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 486:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Church of Rome unmask'd, or her false principles briefly detected with some reasons of so many retaining or returning to communion with her, and the great danger of everlasting destruction, that such persons, especially after separations from her, return to her communion, do run themselves on / written by a learned divine, by way of letter to a friend in the country.</title>
                  <author>Learned divine.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Isaac Cleave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48544:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Church of Rome Unmask'd: OR HER FALSE PRINCIPLES Briefly Detected.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER VVith ſome Reaſons of ſo many retaining or returning to Communion with Her, and the great danger of everlaſting Deſtruction: That ſuch Perſons, eſpecially after ſeparation from Her, return to Her Communion, do run themſelves upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Learned Divine, by way of Letter to a Friend in the Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 4.14, 15, 16, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Enter not into the way of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men. Avoid it, paſs not up it, turn from it, and paſs away. For they ſleep not except they have done miſchief; and their ſleep is taken away unleſs they cauſe ſome to fall. For they eat the Bread of wickedneſs, and drink the Wine of violence.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying, Come out of her (from <hi>Babilon</hi>) my people, that ye be not partakers of her Sins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues. For her Sins have reached unto Heaven, and God hath remembred her Iniquities.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 18.4, 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iſaac Cleave</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Star</hi> next door to <hi>Searjants-Inne</hi> in <hi>Chancery-lane,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48544:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48544:2"/>
            <head>The Fallibility and Falſhood of the Church of Rome, briefly detected and made manifeſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce Providence caſt me ſo luckily into your company and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, your affable carriage and obliging civility, hath ſtirred up in me, both towards your ſelf and your relations, no ſmall affections and affectionate deſires of your beſt welfare and happineſs, and therefore having heard, not without grief, that the Roman party have endeavoured to ſeduce you or them into their communion. I have not been a little exerciſed in my heart with deſires to prevent or reſcue you therefrom, being well aſſured that the Factors for that communion are Deceitful workers, evill doers; ſuch, as the fruit and product of their Principles in them, who are ſnared with them, is no leſs than imminent danger of, if not inevitable deſtruction. And indeed I cannot but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail that any ingenuous perſons brought up under the light of the Scriptures and of Proteſtant doctrine, ſhould have attained to no great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er underſtanding and better judgment thereby, than to be impoſed upon by perſons guilty of ſo much corruption in their Religion, as that a man with half an eye, (as they uſe to ſay) if not careleſs to uſe and improve it for his own welfare, may eaſily diſcern it, but yet I know their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties are great and their inſinuations ſtrong where they can get admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: to obviate which, I ſhall indeavour a little to help you againſt them, and to let you ſee wherein the Roman Church, and the men of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, are ſo dangerouſly erroneous and corrupt, that it behoves all men as they love their ſouls to avoid them.</p>
            <p>And firſt, her claim of Infallibility is a moſt palpable errour and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage, for which ſhe hath neither any good ground nor colour; for what though Chriſt hath ſaid that he will build his <hi>Church</hi> upon the <hi>Rock</hi> and that the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it, yet that affords no more ground for the Roman Church, or any officer in her, to aſſert her or his infallibillity than for any other Church, for granting that by the word, <hi>[It,]</hi> is meant the Church built upon the Rock, and not the Rock it ſelfe upon which he builds it (though the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cam, it,</hi> being a relative agrees in gender with, and may therefore be referred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48544:3"/>
to either of them) yet its Chriſts Church indefinitely and generally that our Saviour aſſerts that of, and the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> and the reſt mentioned in the Scriptures, yea, and beyond what are their mentioned, were every whit as much the Church or of the Church of Chriſt, as the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, they were all equally and indifferently members of the ſame Catholick or Univerſal Church when they were firſt planted, and when the Apoſtles wrote to them; and they were all one as well as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Apoſtles miniſtry, and by Chriſt as going forth with them, built upon the ſame Rock, and ſo they were under the ſame promiſes and in the ſame ſtate of ſafety, for all of them conjunctly made up that Church which was and is the Church of Chriſt in its Catholick and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal capacity: and yet we ſee the other Churches might poſſibly and did actually erre very groſly, as is evident in what is ſaid of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 12 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.3. and the Churches of <hi>Gallatia. Gall.</hi> 1.6. and 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 10. and 5.2.3.4. and where now I pray are the Churches of <hi>Aſia, Epheſus,</hi> and the reſt? have none of them failed or erred grieviouſly? &amp; what promiſe made our Saviour to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> more than to any of them? nay, he made ſuch to ſome of them (as to that of <hi>Philodelphia,</hi> of Keeping her in and from the hour of temptation that ſhould come upon all the earth) as we no where find the like made unto Rome, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.8.9.10. oh how would <hi>Rome</hi> have boaſted her ſelf had ſuch a thing been directed to her or to her Angel! if there be any ſuch to her, where is it written or recorded? And yet the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt Chriſts Church, namely, ſo as to ruin it. Chriſt hath &amp; will have a Church in the World, Maugre all the power and malice of hell, yea, and he may have part of it among thoſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Graecia</hi> that are yet leſt in being, though under great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and not free from corruptions, for they whoever they be that heartily believe Jeſus to be the Chriſt, ſo as ſincerely to imbrace his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and be followers thereof, to the beſt of their skill and power, and keep ſingly thereto, they, even the whole company of them, whoever they be, or how much ſoever outwardly diſperſt, are Chriſts church: the Church built upon the Rock, againſt which the gates of hell ſhall not prevail. And ſuch there are, not only (if there be any ſuch) at Rome, and under her juriſdiction, but more purely and leſs corruptly in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of the world that are no members of her.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid (as I know it is by them) that Chriſt gave a more peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar priviledge to the Church or Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> than to any other Church or Biſhop belonging thereto, as to infallibility, in that it is built upon St <hi>Peter</hi> as its Biſhop, the Biſhops thereof being his ſucceſſors, To that I ſay, that the Scriptures know or uſe no ſuch language as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48544:3"/>
Churches, or any Churches being built or founded upon St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Yea St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf tells us, that the true Believers (and ſo conſequently the Church (<hi>comes to Chriſt the living Stone, diſallowed indeed of men, but cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of God and precious, and are built upon him, ſo us to grow up into a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual houſe, an holy Prieſthood,</hi> &amp;c. not making any mention of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelf, that is to <hi>Peter,</hi> and being built upon him 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>other foundation can no man lay, than that which is laid,</hi> which (he ſaith not is <hi>St. Peter,</hi> not <hi>Petrus,</hi> but <hi>Petra</hi>) is Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>true Rock;</hi> who is the <hi>foundation</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> both that upon which they themſelves were <hi>built</hi> and <hi>ſtood,</hi> and that upon which they as <hi>God's Builders built his Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.11. Epheſ. 2.20. And ſurely no man can ſtand more ſtrongly by being built upon St. <hi>Peter,</hi> than by being built upon Chriſt. Nor find we either Chriſt himſelf or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Apoſtles to ſay or ſignify any ſuch thing, as that the place or Church where <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould reſide or praeſide, ſhould be more Infallible than any other Church or Churches founded, reſided in, or praeſided over by any other of his Apoſtles. Nor that ſuch as ſhould ſucceed him as Biſhops in any place, much leſs in <hi>Rome</hi> praeſided in by him, ſhould be more Infallible than other Biſhops. If the praeſidency of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> can ſecure that Church or it's Biſhop from failing or falling into Errour, how comes it to paſs that his ſitting at <hi>Antioch,</hi> did not alſo ſecure that place &amp; Church? Yea &amp; thoſe Churches of <hi>Judaea</hi> &amp; of the Circumciſion whereof he was the Prime and immediate Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. Surely they ought rather to have had this Privilege and Praerogative from him than <hi>Rome</hi> a Gentile Church, which was rather under S. <hi>Paul's</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas's</hi> Jurisdiction, as being the Apoſtles of the Gentiles. It's ſtrange that none of the Churches more certainly planted by him, ſhould have this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, but only <hi>Rome,</hi> which it is not certain that he planted or ever came into: for ſome of no ſmall learning have made a queſtion of that that I ſay not have poſitively denied it. Surely none but ſimple perſons and ſuch as are eaſy and willing to be deceived, and therefore look not well to their goings, will believe ſuch groundleſs praetexts impoſed upon them. True it is that ſome of the Ancient Councels gave a Patriarchal power to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſubjecting theſe Weſtern Churches thereunto; but that was but an humane conſtitution for order and unities ſake, and gave him no more Infallibility than the like conſtitutions gave to the Biſhops of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or <hi>Antioch,</hi> or <hi>Alexandria,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> whom they made Patriarchs alſo in their reſpective Jurisdictions. Nor yet did that make <hi>Rome</hi> or it's Church the whole Catholique Church, or the Biſhop thereof the Head of it, as is evident by the 6th Councel of <hi>Carthage,</hi> where <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> the Popes Legate, challenging for his Maſter a power to order all great matters in all places, &amp; pretending for it a Decree of the <hi>Nicene</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48544:4"/>
Councel, was upon diligent ſearch into the Records of the ſaid Councel found a falſifyer thereof, and thereupon was decreed an equality in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with the other Patriarchs. But beſide all this, againſt the plea of that Church's Infallibility, it is evident.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That ſhe hath in Fact erred, and can there be a clearer and better demonſtration of the poſſibility of her <hi>Erring,</hi> deceiving and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, than that ſhe hath actually <hi>Erred:</hi> For though <hi>à poſſe ad eſſe non valet conſequentia,</hi> yet <hi>ab eſſe ad poſſe eſt validiſſima.</hi> Now that ſhe hath actually <hi>Erred</hi> is evident not only in her members and different parties, but alſo in her conjunct conſideration, and in her Head. As for her ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>erred</hi> and yet <hi>erring</hi> in her parties and members, it's demonſtrable in this, that <hi>contradictoria non poſſunt eſſe ſimul vera; of two contradictory po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions maintained by different parties; the one muſt needs be falſe.</hi> Now in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> there are contradictory poſitions maintained by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parties; witneſs the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> the one contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting the other in the matter of the immaculateneſs of the conception of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the one denying, and the other aſſerting it; if the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was conceaved in her Mothers womb without ſin, then the <hi>Dominican</hi> Party of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church <hi>errs,</hi> and if otherwiſe, then the <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcan</hi> Party <hi>errs.</hi> The like may be ſaid of the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> in the five Articles wherein they differ. But I ſay not only their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, but their Head and Biſhop may <hi>erre</hi> alſo even <hi>in Cathedrâ,</hi> or in his ſolemn Determinations and doings, yea in matters of Faith; as is made manifeſt in <hi>Liberius,</hi> ſubſcribing to Arrianiſme, and <hi>Vigilius</hi> who both condemned and commanded the ſame things to be believed; as in the three Chapters condemned by a Councel as favouring Neſtorianiſme, and in <hi>Honorius</hi> who was condemned by a Councel for a Monothelite. And ſurely if a Pope may contradict himſelf, and ſay and unſay a thing as Pope and Head of their Church; and both condemn and command the belief of the ſame thing (as in that caſe of Pope <hi>Vigilius</hi>) he muſt needs be Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible and <hi>erre</hi> in the one of them. And there is no way to avoid it, but that either ſome of their Popes have erred, or ſome of their General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels (which is the Church repreſentative, and were ſome time alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and held to be about the Pope, and were uſually conſented to and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by their Popes) have been deceived in condemning them as having <hi>erred:</hi> either of which ſuppoſals mightily infringes the Infallibility of their Church. Nay, and it is believed that the Janſeniſts, would they ſpeak out, do not look upon the late Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> as Infallible in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the five Articles maintained by them. Nay, did not St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himſelf greatly <hi>erre</hi> in a main matter of Faith, and that too after our Saviour had ſaid to him, <hi>Thou art Peter, and upon this Rock will I build my Church,</hi> when he preaches ſuch doctrine to his Maſter, as that <hi>he ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48544:4"/>
not ſuffer death,</hi> for which our Saviour rebuking him, cal'd him Sathan, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.22, 23. But not only have and do great Parties in her and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of her <hi>erre,</hi> and even their Popes themſelves, but She herſelf in her whole Authoratative Conſtitution and Catholique complex conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that very groſly too: if we look upon her Doctrines and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in the light of the infallible teſtimony of God, and of his holy Spirit ſpeaking in the holy Scriptures, which is the Touch-ſtone to which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> or the Lord himſelf by him in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.20. and Chriſt himſelf in <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. directs us; and to which the noble <hi>Boereans</hi> brought the Apoſtle <hi>Paul's</hi> preaching with commendation for their ſo doing, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.12. yea and the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf directs the Churches and the believers therein to that in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. and 3.1, 2. and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> commends <hi>Timothy</hi> for that <hi>from a child he knew the holy Scriptures,</hi> they being <hi>able to make men wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15. implying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that even Children if they will mind the holy Scriptures, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſeek the knowledge of them, may as they grow up in ſome good meaſure obtain it to their great benefit, and ſalvation. Now contrary to theſe holy Scriptures this Church of <hi>Rome errs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In forbidding and witholding from men the reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures both while in childhood and afterwards, which is a manifeſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Chriſt and the holy Spirit, and his faithful Servants, for therein ſhe forbids what they bad and exhorted to, as is ſhewed in what is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaid. They ſaid the Believers <hi>did well to take heed to them,</hi> and willed them <hi>to be mindful of the words of the Prophets,</hi> and the commandments of the Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. and 3.1, 2. And this Church refuſes to let men have them in their own languages that they may read them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally except they will purchaſe a Licenſe with mony, which is the great Goddeſs worſhipped at <hi>Rome.</hi> An evident and plain demonſtration that the deeds of this Church are evil, becauſe ſhe withholds from men the light whereby they ſhould judge of them; and that ſhe leads her Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers into by-paths and ways of error, when ſhe witholds from them what holds forth, and would guide them into the truth. <hi>Chryſoſtom in his time exhorted his hearers to take the Bible into their hands, and call toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Neighbours, and by thoſe holy Oracles to water the minds both of themſelves and them, that they might the better withſtand the wiles of Sathan,</hi> &amp;c. Hom. 6, <hi>in Gen.</hi> But this Church is for taking away theſe weapons of the holy Spirit and divine waterings of their minds from them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In making herſelf the whole Catholique Church, while ſhe ties up mens Salvation to their communion with her, and ſubjection to her Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, which is a groſs and grievous <hi>error;</hi> and all one as to make a part (and that a very unſound too) to be the whole, to the denying in effect this fundamental truth, that whoſoever believeth on Chriſt ſhall be ſaved.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48544:5"/>
For while ſhe maintains that out of the Church there is no ſalvation, and then aſſumes that all that are not in her communion and of her Church are out of the Church, ſhe makes all thoſe Believers in Chriſt however cordial and conſtant they be therein, that are not of her ſociety, to be in the ſtate of damnation: and ſo contradicts Chriſt and his Apoſtles that ſay whoever believes on him ſhall be ſaved, and that there is no reſpect of perſons as to their belonging to this or that place or Church, as to that matter. It was not ſo in the Apoſtles time; for neither the Churches of <hi>Judaea,</hi> nor the ſeven Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> nor the Churches uf <hi>Galatia,</hi> or any other Churches mentioned in the Scriptures diſtinctly from that of <hi>Rome</hi> were ever ſaid or ſignified to be the members of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or to owe any ſubjection to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Nor doth the Apoſtle when he ſaith, <hi>if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth Jeſus the Lord, and with thine heart believeſt that God raiſed him from the dead thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi> put in as a third requiſite to the definition of a right Chriſtian, and an Heir of Salvation if thou acknowledgeſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as the Mother Church, and be ſubject to the Pope or Biſhop thereof, as if without that they were not true Members of the Catholick Church of Chriſt, nor might be ſaved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9. yet this is now an Article of the Roman Creed, wherein they imitate the Donatiſts of old who would confine the Church of Chriſt, and by conſequence Salvation to <hi>Affrica,</hi> and therein to the Men of their Communion as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teſtifies. Surely this is none of the leaſt Errors of the Roman Church but a groſs and grievious one, making Chriſt and his Apoſtles, upon the matter, to be Lyars, and the Scripture ſayings that own all Believers in Chriſt for Members of her Church, to be falſehoods.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In doing contrary to the Apoſtles expreſs direction, that all things in the Church ſhould be done to edification, to which he adds, that if any man judge himſelf a Prophet, or ſpiritual, he ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the things he wrote thereabout to be the commandments of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26, 31. yet theſe men and this Church, contrary hereto, impoſe upon their Members in moſt places yet, and have upon all formerly for divers ages, to perform their Service, or Prayers, and Thankſgivings to God in an unknown tongue, notwithſtanding that the ſame Apoſtle hath expreſly teſtified that the ſo doing is contrary to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.10, 11. to 28. and will we follow men, or joyn our ſelves with them, that ſo palpably and openly contradict the Word and Commandment of God, and ſo loudly proclaim that they fear him not, and believe them when they tell us they are infallible? and though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it may be ſaid that in this and another Nation they do, or are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to permit their Service in an unknown Tongue, yet that excuſeth them not for ſo much as they have all along ſo notoriouſly practiſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48544:5"/>
till of late ſome have extorted this as it were unwillingly from them, nor do they yet acknowledge their error and iniquity in what they have done formerly, but juſtify themſelves in it, by not altering that evil practiſe and impoſition every where; for in <hi>Spain, Italy,</hi> and in many other parts, I ſuppoſe they retain it. Nay Mr. <hi>Egan</hi> a lately converted Fryar, informs us that the Pope forbids the uſe of their Prayers which ſome have turned into the Vulgar Language, ſo as that they that uſe them are not right Roman Catholicks, in his Recantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sermon, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. but if they had reformed this every where, yet even their Reformation would be a Conviction that they have erred therein, and deſtroyed their Plea for Infallibility, whether in their Church formally conſidered, or in their Head the Pope, ſeeing both the one and the other of them have a long time practiſed, allowed, and impoſed ſo groſs a miſcarriage, and taught the people to believe it to be a ſervice acceptable unto God. Can this Church be Infallible that hath fallen and done ſo fowly? or can they be innocent that joyn themſelves in Communion with her, when ſhe ſo much ſlighting and acting impudently in oppoſition to the commandment and directions of Chriſt, and as it were openly diſclaiming therein what his authority injoyns, and practiſes things ſo contrary thereunto; eſpecially how can they but be horribly guilty of caſting away their own Souls, who being brought up under clearer and better light, do willingly depart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, or ſuffer themſelves to be ſeduced into a compliance with her? Surely, ſince it was the deſign of Chriſt to bring light into the world, and to be the Light of the world to direct and guide their Feet into the ways of Peace: and he hath ſet his Church and Servants for lights therein alſo; they who take away that light, or withhold it from them, and lead them into darkneſs, denying them the Scriptures, and teaching them to pray, or rather to ſay Prayers in an unknown ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, wherein they cannot edifie or be edified, they therein declare themſelves to be oppoſite to Chriſt, and ſo to be very Antichriſts. Oh that none of your Souls may come into their ſecret, or have fellowſhip with them; but yet this is not all in which they declare plainly that they erre groſly from the Faith and Truth of Chriſt, and the true way of his Worſhip. Behold it ſtill in other particulars. For,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whereas the Lord Jeſus in the Night in which he was betrayed, inſtituted his Holy Supper, to be Celebrated in commemoration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him. In which He gave to his Diſciples (and ordered his Apoſtles to do the like to the Churches afterwards) a Commemoration of his death and paſſion in two diſtinct Elements of bread and wine, the one before and the other after, and bad them all expreſly drink of the cup, and the Apoſtles plainly tell us, that they delivered to the Churches that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48544:6"/>
which they alſo received of Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo that they both gave the bread to be eaten, and the cup to be drunk by them. Witneſs the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15, 16. Where not directing them to ſome eternal infallible Judge &amp; Determiner of their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; he bids them as wiſe men, to judge of his ſayings, and mentions both the cup of bleſſing which they bleſſed, calling it the communion or fellowſhip (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) of the blood of Chriſt, and the bread that they brake, calling it the communion of the body of Chriſt; and in chap. 11.23, 24, 25, 26. Where repeating the words and order of Chriſts inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Supper in both branches or parts of it, he ſaith, <hi>for as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye ſhew forth the Lords death till he come; and let a man</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> any man of the Church indefinitely, Lay or Clergy, as they are now a days diſtinguiſhed) <hi>examine himſelf and ſo let him eat of this bread, and drink of this Cup.</hi> He ſaith not only let him eat of this bread, but alſo let him drink of this cup. <hi>And whoſoever ſhall eat this bread, and drink this Cup of the Lord unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith alſo in chap. 14.37, as we noted before, that the things He wrote were the Commandments of the Lord, yet this Church of <hi>Rome</hi> moſt audaciouſly, and with a <hi>non obſunt</hi> or notwithſtanding all this, preſume to deny the cup to the Laity, yea and to the Clergy too ſay ſome, if any of them be preſent beſide the Prieſt that celebrates or ſaieth Maſs; making nothing of Gods or Chriſts autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the contrary. Surely therefore to them may moſt truly and fully be applyed thoſe words of our Saviour, ſpoken by him againſt the Scribes and Phariſees in whoſe ſteps they walk, <hi>viz. well hath</hi> Iſaiah <hi>propheſied of you Hypocrites, as it is written, this People honoureth me with their lips, but their hearts are far from me. Howbeit in vain do they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the Commandments of men. For laying aſide the Commandments of God, ye hold the Tradition of men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And full well ye reject the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, that you may keep your own Tradition, making the word of God of none effect, through your Tradition which ye have delivered,</hi> Mar. 7.6, 7, 8, 9, 13. For what is their doctrine of Concomitancy but their own Tradition? wherein they teach their Followers to believe that the Cup is in the bread as it were; the blood of Chriſt is in his body, and they as well taken together, For were they not ſo when Chriſt being yet alive inſtituted the Supper? And after his Reſurrection, when the Apoſtle and the Primitive Chriſtians obſerved it in both kinds. And can the ſuppoſal of both together in one be ſo lively a reſemblance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, and commemoration of his death, as when they are given ſeperately? The end of our Saviours inſtituting, and of the Churches ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving this Ordinance, is to ſhew forth <hi>the Lords death till he come.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. And is not his death more lively ſet forth and repreſented
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48544:6"/>
when the Elements are given apart, and ſo the body repreſented as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it's blood, and the blood as ſeparated from the body, than when both are ſuppoſed to be given together in one. In Chriſts ſtate of death his blood was ſhed forth from his body, and in the ſupper as inſtituted of Chriſt, the cup was given by it ſelf, as a repreſentation of his blood ſhed for the remiſſion of our ſins. So that here is in this bold contradiction to our Saviours precept and practice, both a rejecting of his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a making null the end of his inſtitution, the ſhewing forth of his death. Though yet neither is this all (nor the half of that) in which this bad Church dares to confront the authority of God. For</p>
            <p n="5">5. They alſo leave out in their Catechiſmes the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any Graven Image,</hi> &amp;c. And to make up the number of ten, they divide the laſt into two; both contrary to the expreſs voice and command of God, who gave the ſecond as audibly as any of the reſt, and with more expreſs ſanction by way both of threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning added, as a jealous God, puniſhing the Offenders, and promiſe of bleſſing to them that love him and keep his Commandments, and to the practiſe and manner of the Chriſtian Church in all it's Primitive times. Becauſe they confront Gods Commandment in their practiſe, ſetting up, and injoyning Images, and the Likeneſſes, and the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of things and Perſons to be erected and worſhipped, though God hath expreſly commanded the contrary. Oh audacious Church, and Congregation of evil doers! And can any be ſo blind, as not to ſee pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably in this and the other particulars, that they both can, and do <hi>err?</hi> And how then can it be poſſibly imagined, that they are Infallible? Nay rather verily it is far righter to ſay, that they are incorrigible, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent and impudent in their notoriouſly evil Principles and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. God ſaith, <hi>thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any Graven thing, nor the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or ſimilitude of any thing either in Heaven above, or in the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath—thou ſhalt not bow down to them nor worſhip them:</hi> And theſe men do make the ſimilitude of many things in Heaven and Earth, as of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Saints deceaſed, the Croſs of Chriſt, yea, &amp; as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend of God himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; bow down to them, &amp; worſhip them, &amp; yet they ſay they are innocent, &amp; ſo did the adulterous Church of <hi>Judah, when they upon every high Hill, &amp; under every green tree wandred &amp; play'd the Harlot, yet they ſaid, they were not polluted, they had not gone after</hi> Baalim, <hi>they were innocent, and therefore ſurely Gods anger would turn away from them,</hi> Jer. 2.23,35. Even ſo doth this corrupt and erroneous Church plead not only that ſhe is innocent, but alſo that ſhe cannot <hi>err.</hi> But we ſhall have occaſion to ſay more to this anon. Beſides all this,</p>
            <p n="6">6. What is their Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, but a moſt groſs and palpable <hi>error</hi> againſt the Verdict of Sence, and Reaſon, and the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48544:7"/>
Word of God; &amp; therefore muſt needs be without any ſubſtantial reaſon therefrom. And me thinks it's ſtrange, that men will believe Lies, that are ſo evident and notorious, that their very ſences may convince them thereof. If Chriſt ſhould have told his Diſciples, <hi>that a Spirit hath not fleſh and bones, as they ſee him have,</hi> and yet might impoſe upon their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and make them to believe that to be fleſh and bones upon the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of their ſences, which yet in truth for all that might be other-wiſe, had he not been really, what his Adverſaries falſly accuſed him to be? And what weight would there be in that argument, ſo often made uſe of by the Apoſtles to aſſure us of the truth of their Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> that they were Eye-witneſſes of the things they delivered for truths to the Church, and ſee, and heard, and felt what they teſtified; if things might be quite otherwiſe than the moſt plain and conſtant evidence of them to our ſences repreſent them? Now we may ſee the ſubſtance of bread in the Sacrament, as plainly as our eyes can diſcern any ſubſtance, we may feel it with our hands, taſt it with our mouths, ſmell it with our noſtrils. And when we have ſo many evidences that it is bread, yea, and the word of God, and Scriptures of the Apoſtles call it bread too, as they do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the words of Conſecration, when it is broken, yea and eaten too (for they ſay, <hi>the bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt, and ſo often as ye eat this bread,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 10.16. and 11.26.) to be perſwaded upon this Church's or it's Prieſts authority, that there is no bread there, but the very natural body, and the ſubſtance of the fleſh and bones of Jeſus Chriſt; is the moſt palpable impoſture upon our faith, and the moſt unreaſonable credulity, that ever was heard of, not to be parallel'd in any Hiſtories. Oh but ſay they our Saviour ſaid, <hi>this is my body,</hi> and therefore it muſt be his very natural body. As if our Saviour never ſpake in Parables, or uſed not ſimilitudes and figures in his ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo muſt be underſtood to ſpeak Literally, when the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his words ſo contradicts our ſences, yea, and our reaſon too. For if the ſubſtance of bread be gone, and the very ſubſtance of his body, fleſh, blood, and bones be there really preſent under the forms of bread and wine, upon the Conſecration or pronunciation of thoſe words, <hi>this is my body,</hi> how many abſurdities muſt follow thereupon? As then Chriſt muſt have many bodies diſtinct from one another, or the ſame to be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied beyond all poſſibility to ſay into how many; yea then while Chriſts body ſate by his Diſciples whole and untouched, it muſt be at the ſame inſtant in their hands and mouths, yea his whole body in every one of their hands and mouths in it's mortal ſtate, and yet his whole body viſibly before them all, and diſtinct from them all, and from all their hands and mouths, and what was therein: yea, then his body muſt be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by himſelf before it was broken, and he was as it were his own Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48544:7"/>
before he was crucifyed &amp; ſlain, and while as yet nothing of that nature was done to his body. For if that bread which he took and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed was tranſubſtantiated into his body, then he ſaying of it, that it was broken for them, in that he brake the bread, it muſt then be broken by himſelf, and yet for all it was broken and eaten too, yet it was as whole after that, yea, and in the very time of it's being broken and eaten as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and was taken, and broken, and crucified on the Croſs by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, after every one of his Diſciples had eaten it in it's natural ſubſtance. Then alſo he muſt have a thouſand and a thouſand bodies at once in the ſeveral places where the Maſs is Celebrated, and the Hoſt eaten, and the whole body eaten by every Communicant in it's ſubſtance corporally, &amp; yet his body whole &amp; entire in Heaven; and the Heavens muſt receive or contain it till the time of the reſtitution of all things, ſpoken of by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> Yea and when the Hoſts is reſerved in the <hi>Pix</hi> or Box, the ſame body muſt be in the ſame time in Heaven &amp; Glory, and ſhut up in a narrow box in diverſe places, where poſſibly it may mould; or if the Mice can come to it, be eaten too by them: except the Mice can eat accidents without the ſubſtance, &amp; they can be accidents without ſubſtance to inherein, that are in ſuch caſe mouldy or the like, and all the abſurdities that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets caſt upon the Heathen Idolaters, when they tax them with making a God that cannot help or ſave it ſelf, but may be carried to and fro as men pleaſe; may be all juſtified as rational, or warranted as poſſible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by this one Doctrine. For do not the Prieſts, they ſay, make of a piece of bread the perſon of Chriſt, God and man, even their Maker? And when a Baker hath of the ſame dough made diverſe cakes or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and divers of them being caught and taken and eaten by men, the Prieſt takes one or more of them, and Conſecrates and makes a God of it, and falls down and worſhips it, and perſwades the people to worſhip it, telling them it is very God and their Saviour. Though yet when it is in their hands, it is in their power if they will to caſt it away, or to burn it in the fire, if they ſecretly reſerve it, and it cannot reſcue it ſelf from them and their power, no more than the God made of a piece of a Tree could. May it not as well be ſaid to theſe, as to thoſe Heathen Idolaters, <hi>remember this, and ſhew your ſelves men; bring it again to mind O ye Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors,</hi> Iſai. 46.8. For are not theſe men every whit as much infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as thoſe perſons or worſe. For there they took a piece of a Tree, the workmanſhip of God more immediately, and having burnt part of it in the fire, and roaſted meat and warmed themſelves with it, they made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother part of it into an Image or ſimilitude of ſomething, and ſet it up, and Conſecrated it with ſome words or charms, and then they called it their God, they prayed to it, and ſaid deliver me, <hi>for thou art my God,</hi> Iſa. 44.14, 15, 16, 17. Giving it Divine worſhip. Perhaps they might
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48544:8"/>
think as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do, that after they had Conſecrated it, it was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated too, and ceaſed to be wood; the matter and ſubſtance of that was gone, and it was thenceforth not a Block or wood, but really a God, and had power to help and ſave it's Worſhippers. As the Poet deridingly ſings of their <hi>Priapus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Olim truncus eram ficulnus, inutile lignum,</l>
               <l>Cùm Faber incertus ſcamnum faceret né, <hi>Priapum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Maluit eſſe Deum.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whence it might ſay in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>I ſome time ſince a Block of Figtree was,</l>
               <l>But now I for a God do firmly paſs.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And do not the <hi>Papiſts</hi> after the ſame ſort, while that which was as to it's matter, Corn growing in the field, and after that was reaped, threſhed, ground in the Mill, kneaded in the Trough, and baked in the Oven, ſome parts of the ſame dough or maſs being taken and eaten, another part of it is taken and conſecrated by the Prieſt with ſome words ſaid over it, and then thenceforth it is called, taken for, and worſhipped as God. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon of <hi>Immanuel,</hi> God with us; though it be equally in the hand and power of men to diſpoſe of it as they pleaſe, to caſt it away, or burn it in the fire, as to the power of poſſibility, as the Trunk or ſtock of the Conſecrated Tree was; for it's ſome time ſhut up in a Box, while it may mould. Nay, <hi>Fryar Aegan</hi> in his <hi>Recantation Sermon</hi> preached in <hi>London April</hi> the ſixth 1673. having been Confeſſor General in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Guardian of the <hi>Friory</hi> of <hi>Monaſterioris</hi> in the Province of <hi>Lemſter,</hi> tells us, <hi>pa.</hi> 6th. That <q>coming to a publick houſe to refreſh himſelf, he found that a Lewd Prieſt had pawned the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Hoſt to the woman of the houſe for five &amp; thirty ſhillings (poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly enough as the price of his drunkenneſs, or of ſome worſe prankwith the Hoſteſs) &amp; that he the ſaid <hi>Fryar Aegan</hi> redeemed it with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark (as he ſaith) that Chriſt was made by him not an Offering for ſin, but a Sacrifice for his Luſt.</q> See here if thoſe latter perſons are not worſe than the former, the Heathen Idolaters. For they did not either teare their Block in pieces, when they had made him a God, theſe teare him with their teeth, as the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councel expreſt it, nor did they uſe to pawn them, as this Prieſt pawned what he called his Saviour; ſo as had not the <hi>Fryar</hi> redeemed him, which they worſhip as their Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, might have laine in captivity and bondage, till he had been utterly loſt or ſpoiled. Oh ſottiſh error and ignorance! Oh but our Saviours words, together with the Omnipotency of God muſt be made to bear the burthen of all theſe abſurdities. But why muſt theſe words <hi>(this is my body)</hi> be preſt to ſo undue and abſurd a ſervice, when many others of like import are leſt at liberty therefrom? Did our Saviour call the bread, or that thing he gave his Diſciples, God-man, or did he require
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48544:8"/>
them to kneel down and worſhip it, as theſe men do? That would have been to the purpoſe indeed: but in that he ſaid, <hi>take, eat,</hi> not take, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, this is your God; it may be well apprehended, that they go herein beſides his Warrant, in what they do, and that his words afford no ground for it. Oh but he ſaid, <hi>this is my body,</hi> and he is true, and his words are to be believed. Do theſe men think then, that where ever our Saviour or the Holy Ghoſt calls one thing by the name of another to which it hath ſome reference or relation (as is uſual in Sacramental matters) the thing is tranſubſtantiated into the being and ſubſtance of that thing which it is named? I ſuppoſe not. For then the cup muſt be tranſubſtantiated into the New Teſtament. For our Saviours words are as expreſs in the other part of the Sacrament for that, as they are for this they ſo groſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and impoſe upon the underſtanding of all others; for ſo St. <hi>Luke</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly render and relate his words, <hi>likewiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſupper the Cup, ſaying, this Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hic Calix.</hi> Not this wine, or this that is in this Cup, but this CUP is the New Teſtament. Would the word <hi>[Is]</hi> and the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of God do ſuch a Miracle in the bread, as to tranſubſtantiate it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very body of Chriſt; and will not the ſame do a Miracle here, to tranſubſtantiate the Cup into the New Teſtament. No, but here they are forced to grant a Figure. Though the Omnipotency of God is able to make as great a change upon the golden or ſilver Chalice, as upon the bread. And I ſuppoſe the change is ſomewhat leſs. For the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſomewhat leſs than God himſelf, a Covenant or Will made by him with us. And may not a Divine Writing be as eaſily hid under the form of a ſilver Chalice, as the Chriſt, God man under the form of bread? And yet here they, notwithſtanding Gods Omnipotency and Chriſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſaying, allow a figure in the expreſſions, and leave us the ſubſtance of the Cup entire, and command not men to worſhip that: thinking that by the Cup is meant that in the Cup, though they think (or would have others ſo ſimple as to think) that what is in the Cup, is tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated into the blood of Chriſt that was ſhed for us, and not into the New Teſtament; and ſo that the Diſciples drunk the blood of Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and verily out of that Cup, though it was all, as then, in his veins. But there is no more ground for their impoſing the one than the other, the wine more than the Cup except that it's their pleaſure ſo to do; for both St. <hi>Luke</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> render it ſo, <hi>this Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood;</hi> and they ſpake certainly the words and mind of Chriſt, as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as St. <hi>Mathew</hi> and St. <hi>Mark,</hi> who render them, <hi>thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is the Blood of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he New Teſtament,</hi> and God is as able to effect the one as the other; and the one is no leſs abſurd than the other. For if the wine in the cup or what was ſo, be now really and ſubſtantially blood, even that blood, that was ſhed out of Chriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de for us. Muſt not then the blood of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48544:9"/>
while his body is in Heaven be really and ſubſtantially ſeparated from his body: and ſo his body in Heaven is a bloodleſs body, as oft as the Prieſt Conſecrates the Cup, and drinks what is in it: or do they ſay that the body is in and with the blood, as they ſay the blood is in the bread or body, and therefore that alone is enough to be given to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If ſo, then fleſh, and blood, and bones, and all are in the Chalice too. And no marvel then that they give not the Cup to the people, if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve verily that the fleſh and bones of Chriſt are in it, even the ſame that was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and hung upon the Croſs. Nay, it's rather to be marvelled, how the Prieſt dare venture upon them all to ſwallow them down. They might as eaſily believe, that the matter of the Cup be it ſilver or gold, is turned into the New Teſtament, and become a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Hand-writing of God, though it appear ſtill to our ſences to be a cup, as that the Prieſt ſwallows down his throat, or the people eat very fleſh &amp; bones: and the ſame Miracle and Omnipotency will make the one as poſſible as the other. Or that the ſame thing that is ſhut and hung up in the <hi>Pix,</hi> being a Conſecrated Hoſt, is the ſame numerical body that is glorified and gloriouſly appears in Heaven, &amp; alſo what was eaten by the people in their receiving &amp; eating what of it was given them. But we may ſee how theſe men ſtraining the words of Chriſt where they pleaſe (as they do alſo ſome expreſſions of the Ancient Fathers) make the word of God ſubject to their wills and pleaſures, and where they pleaſe they will grant a Figure, and where they pleaſe, they ſhall be properly and literally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; yea, and ſtrained beyond their litteral expreſſion (for Chriſt ſaid no ſuch thing as, this is tranſubſtantiated into or is the ſubſtance of my very body, as they ſay) though the like abſurdities following upon the litteral ſence of or collection from it, as would from taking the other expreſſions litterally, makes it neceſſary to underſtand them figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſacramentally in the one place as well as in the other. It's true that in this Supper, Chriſt would have us (and it's neceſſary for us) to abſtract or withdraw our minds from the conſideration of the bread and wine in their own proper ſubſtances, and to fix them only upon the body and blood of Chriſt, whereof they are a communion or communication [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] and ſo to have no more to do with thoſe Elements in our thoughts in a manner, than as if there were no ſuch matters: only as they may occaſion us to meditate and conſider that his fleſh <hi>is meat indeed,</hi> the true bread, and everlaſting nouriſhment of our Souls: and his blood or the New Teſtament confirmed by it. Drink indeed, a moſt comfortable matter of refreſhing for the Soul, to take into it's believing conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo ſpiritually and ſacramentally to feed upon his fleſh and blood. But to impoſe upon peoples Faith, that the things which they ſee with their eyes to be very bread and wine, are very Chriſt, his very fleſh and blood, yea God-man, their Saviour; and to cauſe them to worſhip them,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48544:9"/>
is a very groſs departure from and abuſe of Chriſt's inſtitution, and of his command for our obſervation of it. And why may they not as well impoſe upon mens faith, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> after he Confeſſed Chriſt, was tranſubſtantiated into a hard ſtone, and his fleſh, blood, and bones; yea his Soul, and body, and all was metamorphiz'd into a Rock. For our Saviour ſaid unto him, <hi>Tues Petrus,</hi> in the <hi>Syriac [Cephas]</hi> which in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Language ſignifies a ſtone, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. with <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.42. here is Chriſts aſſertion as plainly of <hi>Peter</hi> as there, of the bread. And if the word <hi>[Eſt, is]</hi> imply the ſubſtantial change of the bread in the one, why may not the word <hi>[Es, thou art]</hi> imply the ſubſtantial change of <hi>Simon Bar-Jonah</hi> in the other? And why may it not be as rationally believed, that his fleſh, and bones, yea Soul and body were immediately and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially turned into ſtone, living ſtone, as that the bread was changed into the body of Chriſt ſubſtantially; ſeeing the Omnipotency of God was as well able to do the one as the other. And that is pleaded as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for our Faith to believe this. And ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> was a living walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stone, that had not the ſubſtance of either fleſh, or blood, or bones in him, though the appearance of them all to the ſences. Yea, and why may it not be as well impoſed upon mens Faith, that Chriſt himſelf is ſo changed in his ſubſtance into ſtone too. For he is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtone,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.4. and that the Altar, that <hi>Jacob</hi> built at <hi>Shechem</hi> was tranſubſtantiated into the Eſſence of God, becauſe <hi>Jacob</hi> Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it called it <hi>El Elohe, Iſrael, God, the God of Iſrael,</hi> Gen. 33.20. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are ſtrangely infatuated or obſtinately wilful, that cannot or will not ſee the abſurdity of this Doctrine of theirs, ſo contrary both to ſence and reaſon, and ſo void of any ſolid ground for it in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Oh but they will ſay, they are the Church, and their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be taken as the infallible truth, and therefore if they did aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the like changes and tranſubſtantiations in other things, then they were to be believed too. For our Faith is to be reſolved into their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as our Saviour tells us, that, <hi>they that hear not the Church, are to be accounted as Heathens and Publicans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But to that it's ſaid and ſhewed before, that they are not the Church Catholique, but only a part of the Church, and a very corrupt part too. To which I add, that I find it injoyned to us, that we ſhould hear Chriſt, the great Prophet of God, in all things which he ſhall ſay unto us, but I find it no where injoyned us, that we ſhould hear the Church in all that ſhe ſhall ſay unto us. And that the Scripture here quoted by them to ſerve their deſign, is perverted by them from it's true and genuine intent rnd ſcope. For our Saviour did not there intend nor ſpeak any thing, as ſignifying an intent to teach us to build our Faith or belief of the Scripture-ſayings, or the Expoſition of the Scripture, upon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48544:10"/>
the Authority of the Church, or it's ſayings, much leſs of any upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt party, that unduely challenge to themſelves the title and appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Church, much leſs the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is evidently about offences, given by any ſinning Brother, which being evident in themſelves, might by any particular perſon againſt whom they were committed, be reprehended and faulted, and in caſe the party offending would not hear a private admonition, then it ſhould be reproved by the ſame perſon again, taking one or two perſons as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes with him, who might alſo join in reproving or admoniſhing him. And if ſtill he harden his heart, and retain his offenſive or evil way or practice, then they ſhould declare it to the Church, who might all teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their diſlike, or give him a joint admonition of the ſame fault. And if he hear not them, in ſuch joint admonition given them by the Church, then the offended Brother might diſclaim communion with him, and leave him as no more to be owned by him than an Heathen man or a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican. Here is nothing of the Church's giving the object of faith to be believed, or of her being to be heard in whatſoever ſhe ſhall ſay, though never ſo contrary to ſence or reaſon, or to the Scripture ſayings, or to the commands of God and Chriſt; but of the Chuch's admoniſhing an offending Brother, who being admoniſhed by her ought to hear the Church therein. But that's in no other thing, than in what he ought to have heard firſt the offended Brother in, upon his own private admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or the offended Brother with one or two joining with him, upon his ſlighting the admonition given by the offended Brother alone. But ſurely no private Brother, nor any one or two with him is to be heard in whatever he or they may give out for truth or matter of faith whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it agree with the Scriptures, and the commands of God and Chriſt or not; or put abſurd expoſitions upon the Scriptures, that may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by common ſence. And therefore neither ſpeaks it there of any ſuch authority given to the Church to give ſuch interpretation, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition laid upon any to receive ſuch an interpretation given by any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that name. Nor indeed by the Church can be meant there the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church all over the World, much leſs is it tyed up to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> except in it's proper Jurisdiction: but it's meant evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently of the particular ſociety or congregation or Church, to which ſuch an offending Brother belongs. For it is ſuch a Church as any offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Brother, his private admonition being rejected, may inform of the offence, and that upon the information given, may alſo admoniſh the offender, which can neither be done to or by the Catholique Church in it's Catholique and extenſive capacity, no nor yet to or by the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> as to the caſe of every or any offender to whom this rule ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains (as to what is obſervable in caſe of ſcandal and offence) that live in places remote from <hi>Rome</hi> and her Jurisdiction. Surely our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48544:10"/>
no where ſignifies that perſons living in <hi>Judaea</hi> or <hi>Galilee</hi> ſhould go or ſend up information againſt an offending Brother as far as <hi>Rome.</hi> Nor find we that in any diſſentions in the Churches, any of the Apoſtles left any ſuch orders in any of their Epiſtles; however <hi>Rome</hi> may have challenged or deſired ſuch homage and honour to be done to her, and hath put men upon ſuch unreaſonable and chargeable burthens, ſince the times of her uſurpations upon the World. Her challenging that authority and homage to be done to her, is but what the falſe Prophets of the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> calling themſelves the Church or holy City, were wont to do. And therefore being forewarned by the Apoſtles (even by St. <hi>Peter</hi> from whom the <hi>Pope</hi> pretends to derive his power) that there ſhould be falſe Teachers in the Chriſtian Church or Churches now, that would imitate and do like thoſe falſe Prophets, we are concerned to ſtand upon our watch, and when we diſcern any party taking that courſe, and walking in their ſteps, not to give heed to them. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, that as there were <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> formerly <hi>among the people, ſo there would be falſe Teachers among</hi> the Chriſtian People, that would <hi>bring in damnable Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> going beſide the Scriptures, for that properly the word tranſlated privily, with reference to what was ſaid before, imports: He had commended them before for <hi>taking heed to the ſure word of Propheſie, as to a Light ſhining in a dark place; even the Prophets that came in old time by the will of God:</hi> wherein <hi>the holy Men of God ſpake as they were moved or carried by the Holy Ghost,</hi> the Scriptures of the Prophets. Now theſe falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers going beſides or contrary to them, would bring in Hereſies of damnation, <hi>denying the Lord that bought them.</hi> For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, they ſhall bring in;</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is often either <hi>contrà</hi> or <hi>praeter, againſt</hi> or <hi>beſides;</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>contrary to the Law,</hi> Act. 18.13. and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>is either contray to or beſides what we have preached,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>is contray to or beſides what ye received, or rather to what ye have otherwiſe received</hi> namely than as the falſe Apoſtles taught them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. And ſo the ſenſe is, that theſe falſe Teachers ſhould or would bring in damnable Doctrines or Hereſies contrary to or beſides (that is differing from) the forementioned Scriptures, ſwarving from or oppoſing their ſayings. And ſuch we find) and have mentioned ſome of them, and we may inſtance in more) brought in and maintained by the Papiſts. Now the falſe Prophets of old a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, to whom theſe falſe Teachers are compared, and made to anſwer (as the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>even as there ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be among you falſe Teachers,</hi> imply) were oftentimes the greateſt and Prevailing party of the Prophets among the people; ſuch as the generality, even the Kings, Princes, and multitude of the people uſually followed, as appears in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.15, 16. and 29.9, 10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48544:11"/>
5.31. and 14.13. and 23.9, 30, 31, 32. and 26.8, 11. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.14. and 4.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. and 22.25, 28. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.4. And thence it was that the true Prophets were evil ſpoken of and traduced, yea, Perſecuted and ſlain by them; as if they had been falſe Prophets and ſeducers, as is to be ſeen in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.30. and 20.2. and 29.26, 27. and 37.13, 14, 15, 19, 38.4, 6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.29, 30, 31, 37. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.52. Even as here the falſe Teachers are ſuch, and ſo received as that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the multitude, or many it's ſaid ſhall follow their pernicious ways, ſo as the way of truth which is agreeable to the Scriptures of the Prophets, and the commandments of the Apoſtles, ſhall be evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, reproached and caſt out as Hereſie; as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and it's Teachers caſt out the commands and ſayings of Chriſt and the Scriptures in many things, and the way that is agreeable thereto, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it Hereſie, and them that ſtick thereto Hereticks. Now it was the way of the falſe Prophets whom theſe falſe Teachers, which in theſe laſt days men have heaped up or multiplied by heaps to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (that is in abundance, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> propheſied they would do, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.) do imitate; that they uſed to ſay that they were the perſons that had the Law with them; and that therefore were to be liſtened to and followed, as thoſe to whom the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it were committed, and from whom it was to be received, and that the true Prophets (who clave to God and his word indeed) were not to be hearkned to, but perſecuted and puniſhed for contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting them. That this was the way of thoſe falſe Prophets, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in that they ſaid, <hi>we are wiſe, and the Law of the Lord is with us,</hi> Jer. 8.8. Juſt thus ſay the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and it's Teachers, we are the wiſe men, we have the Law and Scriptures with us, we are the true Interpreters of it, and ye muſt take it from our mouths. But the Prophets of God reproved thoſe falſe Prophets and the people as joined with and led by them, ſaying <hi>how ſay ye we are wiſe and the Law of the Lord is with us—the wiſe men are aſhamed—for lo they have rejected the word of the Lord, and what wiſdom is there in them?</hi> Even they that ſaid they were wiſe, and that the Law of the Lord was with them had in truth rejected the word of the Lord, and therefore were deſtitute of true wiſdom, <hi>and dealt falſly from the Prophet to the Prieſt,</hi> verſ. 9, 10. Even ſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and it's Teachers reject the word of the Lord, as is evident in the inſtances we have given, and yet they ſay the Law, the Scriptures and it's Expoſition are with (that is, belong unto) them. They are they from whom men muſt receive it, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom they muſt depend for it. Yea, they do as the falſe Church in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.1, 2. is ſaid to have done; who <hi>make mention of the name of the Lord, but not in truth nor in righteouſneſs; though they called themſelves of the holy City,</hi> that is in effect, the holy Catholick Church. The like is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48544:11"/>
timated of them in <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. where the perſecutors of the Lord's Prophets that were ſuch in truth, yet ſaid of themſelves, <hi>come let us deviſe devices againſt Jeremiah,</hi> and add, as if they had thence authority to do ſo, <hi>for the Law ſhall not periſh from the Prieſt, nor counſel from the wiſe, nor the word from the Prophet.</hi> Now when we ſee or may ſee by the Scriptures of truth, and the teſtimony of the Holy Spirit in them, that there ſhould be falſe Teachers among the Chriſtians anſwerable to the falſe Prophets among the <hi>Jews,</hi> that would bring in Doctrines ſwarving from the Scriptures; and find that the Papiſts and their Teachers evidently do ſo, their challenge of authority to be the ſole Expounders of the Scriptures ſhould nothing move us, while we ſee that they therein walk in the ſteps of the falſe Prophets, eſpecially ſeeing alſo that they challenge an authority which the Holy Ghoſt hath not given them, nor directed his followers any where unto. For the Holy Ghoſt himſelf who led the Apoſtles <hi>into all truth,</hi> Joh. 16.13. doth not in any Scripture teſtifie to us of <hi>Rome</hi> or the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that we ſhould derive our Faith from her, or reſolve it into her or her Doctors, more than into any other Church. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> whoſe authority they pretend to have committed to them (but without any evidence of the holy Scriptures) and whoſe Succeſſors they tell us their Popes or Biſhops are) could not leave more autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to them than he had exerciſed himſelf. Now we find him expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preferring the authority of the Scriptures before his own ſaying or teſtimony as to the reſolution of other mens Faith. Yea, he as well as other Apoſtles proved his ſayings by the holy Scriptures, as is evident in his Epiſtles, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6, 7. and 3.10, 11, 12. and obtruded nothing upon men on his own authority barely, as the Popes preſume to do. He calls <hi>the word of Propheſy a more ſure word,</hi> than what he rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his own knowledge, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18, 19. and inſtead of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the Believers after his death to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and her Biſhops (which ſurely he would and ought to have done had he known of any power given of Chriſt to her or to them, for reſolving mens doubts, and determining their Faith, and exerciſing a dominion over mens conſciences, more than to other Churches or their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops) yea, or directing them to himſelf more than to the reſt of the Apoſtles, when he forewarned them of falſe Teachers &amp; Scoffers that would come in the laſt days: He ſtirs up the Believers minds to remember the words of the Prophets, and the Commandments of the Apoſtles of our Lord and Saviour. He ſaith not his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or his rather than of the other Apoſtles, but indefinitely of the Apoſtles puting in himſelf with them as one of the ſame rank, and of no ſuperior rank or authority among or over them, much leſs doth he ſay that we ſhould after his death be take our ſelves to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48544:12"/>
the Church or Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for our direction, guidance, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from the Error of the wicked, but directs us to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Prophets and Apoſtles, the things ſpoken and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in and by them. He thought not of the Lord <hi>Peter,</hi> or the Lord <hi>Pope;</hi> nor ſignified that the reſt of the Apoſtles ſtood in relation more than himſelf to any man as their Lord, but only to him who is the Saviour. Yea, and the Lord Jeſus himſelf when afterward he appeared to <hi>John</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Patmos,</hi> and gave him viſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations of the things that ſhould come to paſs in the world, and unto the Churches, directed him not to bid us go to <hi>Rome</hi> for reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of our hearts in the matters of God, and in what concerns our preſervation in his truth; but he in his ſeveral Epiſtles to the Churches bids, <hi>Let him that hath an ear hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi> He bids not, <hi>That he that hath an ear ſhould hear the Churches ſimply,</hi> no, nor yet <hi>what the Spirit ſaith in the Churches;</hi> much leſs ſaith he, <hi>Let him that hath an ear hear what the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>ſaith,</hi> or, <hi>what her Biſhop as an heavenly Oracle, or the Spirit, as either in it or him, as Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly tied to his Chair, ſhould dictate to us.</hi> And yet (which is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable) this Book of the Revelations, according to the moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick teſtimonies of Antiquity, was written after the Deaths of all the other Apoſtles, and its probable at leaſt, that he lived not long after it himſelf who was the Penman thereof; and therefore if there were any judge or orderer of mens faith infallible to be looked to by all Churches, beſides the holy Scriptures of the Prophets and Apoſtles, or any Infallible Interpreter of them above the reſt to be taken heed to, it had been the proper place and time ſurely for Chriſt the faithful and true witneſs of God, the <hi>Amen,</hi> the firm and ſure friend and Paſtour of his Church, to have ſignified who it is, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the Church, and every one that hath an ear to hear, and hearken to him, but neither when he was asked, or there was a ſtrife among the Apoſtles who of them ſhould be the greateſt; did he tell them <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould be their Prince and chief among them, nor did he direct them here to any Succeſſor of his at <hi>Rome</hi> or elſewhere, as an infallible Guide and Head to them: no, there is no other Director as to matters of Faith and Worſhip, directed to of God by his Holy Spirit in any Scripture as our abſolute and infallible Guide, but only the Spirit himſelf as ſpeaking in and by the Scriptures to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, what the Scripture ſaith, being called the ſaying of the Holy Ghoſt or Spirit, as is to be ſeen, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7. and 10.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 28.25. And ſurely they are guilty of horrible Idolatry that prefer the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, Word, or Determination of any perſon or perſons, Church or Biſhop, before or above; yea, or but as equal with the teſtimony of the Holy Ghoſt, to caſt by his ſayings or commands, to liſten to,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48544:12"/>
and be ruled by men, is indeed to have the fear of God taught us by mens precepts, and in vain to honour God, or worſhip him, which was the fault of the Jewiſh Church, reproved by the Holy Ghoſt in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> for which alſo he threatned to give up their wiſe and prudent men, on whom the people leaned, to an infatuation of their underſtandings, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. and the fault charged by our Saviour on the Scribes and Phariſees, and the Jewiſh Church, as depending on them, <hi>Math.</hi> 15.1, 3, 7, 8, 9. Mark 7.6, 7. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. and it will be as great or a greater evil in us, than in them if we make our ſelves guilty of it, in as much as God having now ſpoken to us by his only begotten Son, hath declared his Name more plainly and expreſly than he had done in former ages; and therefore greater heed and acquieſcence in his words and ſayings, is expected from us; for us then to forſake the fountain of Living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, (which is Chriſt ſpeaking in his Servants, the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in the Scriptures) to dig up Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns, (as all men with their inventions and decrees, and all their authority and power that are not his, are) would be a more aſtoniſhable madneſs, than what of that nature was practiſed under <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets by the Church of <hi>Iſrael, Jer.</hi> 2.12, 13. Our Saviour in the Relation of the Rich man, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> introduces <hi>Abraham,</hi> directing the Rich mans five brethren to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and not to the Jewiſh <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> or High-Prieſt; or any other perſons claiming an infallible authority diſtinct from them (though they might have had more colour by far for claiming ſuch a thing, either from that in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8.11.13. appointing men in caſe of doubt or controverſy to ſtick to, and obſerve the determinations of the High-Prieſt, or chief Ruler of the People; or from that promiſe in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. where God promiſeth to put his Spirit upon <hi>Zion,</hi> or ſome perſons in it, and his words into their mouth, ſo as to continue it from generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to generation, than any the Pope or the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can ſhew for their claim, yet I ſay <hi>Abraham</hi> directs them to no ſuch perſon or perſons, but onely to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets) and if he ſo directed them then, ſurely now that we have Chriſt and his Apoſtles alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a compleatment of the revelation of Gods mind and will, and as infallible Interpreters of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, it behoves us to take heed to them, as ſpeaking in their words and writings, and not to neglect or refuſe them under pretence of inſufficiency in them to direct us now aright, without ſome other infallible Guide that he no where directs us to, to determine us. And that <hi>Rome,</hi> or her Head the Pope, is not Infallible in her doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation (the thing laſt inſiſted on) is evident from hence, that <hi>Gelaſius</hi> one of their Popes or Biſhops, hath taught the Church that the bread in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48544:13"/>
Sacrament is not <hi>naturû</hi> or <hi>ſubſtantiâ mutatus,</hi> changed in its nature or ſubſtance: and others of them have taught and determined that it is ſubſtantially changed, ſo as the fleſh of Chriſt it is that is eaten and torn with the Teeth of the Communicants, as in the <hi>Luteran</hi> Council was defined, and in <hi>contradictories</hi> one part muſt needs be falſe, which things duly conſidered, may imbolden us to reject the Pleas and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of that Church as more groundleſs Uſurpations &amp; Inchroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which they pervert men from the right ways of God, which our Lord Jeſus hath delivered to us.</p>
            <p>Nay, our Lord Jeſus in the Book of the Revelations, inſtead of directing us to <hi>Rome,</hi> doth clearly call us off from it, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed that to us concerning her, which being taken heed to by us, will admoniſh us to flee from her, for by the concurrent conſent of Interpreters, as led to it by the Scripture it ſelf, compared with the ſtate and condition of <hi>Rome:</hi> it is <hi>Rome</hi> deciphered in that Book, not by the Name of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the beloved City of God, in the light whereof the Nations of the ſaved ſhould walk, but by the name of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Enemy of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and her Inhabitants, and the ſubject of the deepeſt died ſins, and heavieſt judgments mentioned in that Book. Yea, the Papiſt writers themſelves are alſo forced to confeſs the truth hereof it is ſo palpable and evident, (yea, rather than they will not prove St. <hi>Peter</hi> to have been at <hi>Rome, Babylon</hi> ſhall ſignifie <hi>Rome</hi> too in his 1. Epiſtle 5.13.) ſurely ſhe was the City that then ruled over the Kings of the Earth, and was built upon ſeven Hills or Mountains, and that's the City called <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 17.9, 18. and its evident that ſhe ruled over the Kings of the Earth, not only in her Pagan, but alſo as much or more in her Papal State, wherein their Popes or Biſhops have exacted Homage of them, made them kiſs their Toes, hold their Stirrups, wait at their Doors, and do things far below their Majeſty and Grandeur in ſubjection to them. Now in all that Book no good is ſpoken of <hi>Babylon,</hi> nor any direction is given to Gods people, the followers of the Lamb to reſort to her for any thing, but much is ſpoken of its Wickedneſs, Whoredom, Idolatry, Bloodineſs, while it remains, and of its woe and miſery irreparable in its fall, as that that ſhall for ever Periſh, with expreſs and vehement command to Gods people that are in her, to come out of her, leſt pertaking with her in her ſins, they ſhould alſo pertake with her in her Plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. which one conſideration alſo quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws that corrupt interpretation that would confine what is ſaid of her to her Heathen ſtate only, as the Papiſts to excuſe themſelves do, or rather to blind themſelves from ſeeing their own guilt; for if it were ſo then, ſhe ſhould have found her not as a City or Harlot deſtroyed for ever; but by a glorious Metamorphoſis or diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48544:13"/>
of the Spirit of Whoredom, and Reſurrection from her falls in Heatheniſm, changed into the holy City, or the Lambs Wife, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is not the leaſt intimation of any ſuch thing, but a vehement aſſertion of her ſinking like a mighty ſtone in the waters, never to riſe again, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.21. whence it is evident, (which I ſhall mention as a farther diſtinct charge, and a farther inſtance not only of her fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, but alſo that ſhe is fallen foully already in that it is thereby evident) That</p>
            <p n="7">7. She is guilty of Idolatry, for that's it that in Scripture is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by Whoredom; and ſhe is called the great WHORE, and the Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the earth. And ſhe is certainly as great a WHORE from Chriſt, as ever the old <hi>Babilon,</hi> or the old Pagan <hi>Rome</hi> was, and more truly ſo alſo, being not ſo eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed to Chriſt in her Pagan ſtate as ſince ſhe turned Chriſtian. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhe is a Myſtical WHORE, corrupted from the purity of the Faith and Worſhip of God in Chriſt, yet giving out herſelf to be a Queen and Lady, the Queen or Darling of Heaven, the only Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and Infallible Church. In her Pagan ſtate ſhe was more openly and groſly a Harlot, a groſs Idolatreſs, and there was not Myſtery writ on her forehead; but now as very and as arrant an Harlot or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatreſs as then, but more ſpiritually ſuch, and under finer preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. That we may make good this charge againſt her, let us firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and take notice what Idolatry is in the Scripture language. For as it is no asking a mans partner whether he be a Thief, ſo neither will the Adultreſs confeſs her ſelf to be ſuch a one, <hi>but ſhe eateth and wipeth her mouth, and ſaith I have done no wickedneſs,</hi> Prov. 30.20. Now Idolatry in the Scripture language is with reference to the worſhip of God what Fornication or Adultery is among men; therefore it's often compared to and illuſtrated by the practices of Whores and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. and 3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. and 23. and ſo as ſhe is a Whore that takes into the bed of love with her, and proſtitutes herſelf to any man that is not her husband eſpouſed and married to her, whether it be her ſervant, friend, or a ſtranger; ſo he is an Idolater that falls down, and gives religious worſhip to any beſide the true God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be with the heart-worſhip only, or whether alſo or only with the body. In the former way Covetouſneſs is Idolatry, becauſe it's a putting riches in the place of God, as to inward eſtimation of, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to, confidence in them, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Coll.</hi> 3.5. Some alſo make their Belly their God, and commit Idolatry therewith, while they prefer their Belly before God and his favour, and love in Chriſt, or his word and Spirit directing us to worſhip him, and walk with him rightly in and by Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. whether by the Belly be meant the groſſer appetites and brutiſh ſenſual luſts in gluttony, drunkenneſs, intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48544:14"/>
unchaſtity and the like; or elſe their own wiſdom, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and will, the Belly being often uſed to ſignifie and put for the inward man or heart, and what is therein, as in <hi>Job</hi> 32.18, 19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.38. <hi>Job</hi> 15.2, 35. and 20.15, 20. <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.8. and 26.22. Now that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is guilty of Idolatry in thoſe or ſome of thoſe ways of it, what can be more evident. For her covetouſneſs is inſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able graſping or gaping after Crowns, &amp; Scepters, Kingdoms, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, ſo (as was ſaid of the <hi>Caldaean Babilon) that ſhe enlargeth her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire as Hell, and is as Death, and cannot be ſatisfied, but gathers to her all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and heaps up to her</hi> (as far as ſhe can) <hi>all people,</hi> Habak. 2.5. and this that ſhe might be enriched with their worldly riches and treaſures. So as it may be ſaid of her, that ſhe <hi>is abundant in treaſures, and in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of her covetouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 50.13. Yea, and (was ſaid ſometime of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiakim</hi> in <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.17.) <hi>that her eyes and her heart is not but for her cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and to ſhed innocent blood.</hi> Thence the Proverb, <hi>omnia</hi> Romae <hi>venalia, that all things may be ſold at</hi> Rome <hi>for mony;</hi> and the very Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of her name are the Initials of <hi>Radix Omnium Malorum Avaritia.</hi> And as for her Voluptuouſneſs, Uncleanneſs, Sodomy, and Filthineſs, their Church and City is too notoriouſly full of ſuch things, witneſs the lives and doings of diverſe of their Popes and Biſhops, and their taking mony for the open maintainance of Stews and Brothelhouſes, and for her preferring her wiſdom, will, and inventions before the word and appointments of God and Chriſt. What is ſaid before may in part give evidence. So that in theſe things ſhe is a notorious Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, though as if we aske any of the covetous, Epicures, or Self-conceited Perſons, whether they be Idolaters, they will deny it ſtifly, and if we charge them therewith they will be angry; ſo it is with <hi>Rome</hi> and her Church alſo. But again, the giving external religious undue adoration to any thing or perſon that is not God, is Idolatry, as is evident from the Scriptures. For ſo the falling down to the Molten Calf and worſhipping or adoring it, is called Idolatry in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7. though it was profeſſedly in honour of <hi>Jehovah, Exod.</hi> 32.5. ſo alſo was the falling down to the Stock and worſhipping it in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.15. And God in the ſecond Commandment forbids both the <hi>making to our ſelves any graven or carved thing</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>or the likeneſs of any thing</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>in Heaven above or in the Earth beneath,</hi> &amp;c. ſo as to fall down to and worſhip it. Yea, in the <hi>Greek</hi> it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>thou ſhalt not bow down to it, neither ſhalt thou worſhip it,</hi> either of them, <hi>viz.</hi> either to bow down to it, or worſhip it, is Idolatry, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to any ſimilitude made any way, either by carving, graving, painting, or the like by men. And when the holy man <hi>John</hi> fell down to the Angel that ſhewed him the things revealed to him in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, he was twice forbid to do it, and bid to worſhip God, as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48544:14"/>
implying that the worſhipping or bowing down to the Angel was a dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating from and a ſin againſt the Commandment that bids us to worſhip God He might not it ſeems join the worſhip of an Angel to or with the worſhip of God. Nor is it ſaid that he fell down [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] but only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to kneel down to or adore him. Yet it was a thing forbidden him as injurious to God and his worſhip, as intrenching upon his prerogative therein, and ſo certainly reducible to the ſin of Idolatry; even as for a married woman to admit to bed to her ſome of her ſervants, though the chief about her husband, yea, though they be his familiar Friends, it would be Adultery as really as if ſhe ſhould admit meer ſtrangers or enemies to him. Nor would it be an acceptable plea to him that ſhe ſhewed therein the greater honour and humble reſpect to him that ſhe loved his friends and ſervants ſo well for his ſake as to admit them to bed with her alſo, and judged her ſelf too low for his fellowſhip, and therefore thought it meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to honour him after that manner, by contenting her ſelf, at leaſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, with them; hoping that way to make them her greater friends to him from whom alone ſhe expects all her maintainance, though by their mediation ſhe hoped to have more of it and much better. Nor would a King take it well that ſome Homage proper to himſelf, in which the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power is aſcribed to him, ſhould be given out of pretended reſpect to him, to ſome of his Nobles or Courtiers alſo. Now that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is groſly guilty of the giving this ſolemn religious proſtration and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration to thoſe that are not God, is ſo openly and evidently true, that nothing can be more true. For what do they in worſhipping God do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that they do not to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or to ſome other Creatures? Certain it is that neither the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> nor any of the deceaſed Apoſtles or Martyrs, or holy Men, are God; much leſs the Images, Pictures, or Statues of any of them; nor the Croſs, or the Picture, or Image of it, no, nor the Picture or Image of Chriſt himſelf. Nor is the Bread in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God, for that may be ſhut up in a <hi>Pix</hi> or Box, ſo as God cannot be. Yet to all theſe things and diverſe more they fall down and worſhip them with that kind of worſhip forbidden in the words [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>thou ſhalt not fall down to them;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>worſhip God</hi>] Yea, what worſhip the Idolaters uſed to perform to their Idols, graven Images, or Stock of a tree made a God to them, that they perform to others that are not God; that is, they fall down and pray to them to do ſuch things for them, as only God can do, only they ſay not to or of them perhaps that they are their Gods. Nor will their diſtinction of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> excuſe them; for both are forbidden to any but God in a religious way of worſhip or adoration. Therefore the Heathens are faulted for <hi>ſerving thoſe things that by nature are not God,</hi> Gal. 4.8. Where the Apoſtle ſaith, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ye ſerved or performed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to thoſe things that by nature are not God. They were no doubt guilty therein of Idolatry; though it's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48544:15"/>
by that kind of worſhip which the Papiſts by their diſtinction al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelves to give to what by nature is not God. As none of thoſe things before mentioned are by nature God. None of them can ſay that either Angels or glorified Saints, much leſs their Statues or Images are by nature God, by the Apoſtles deſcription of Idolatry, then in which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents it as a giving <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to or ſerving religiouſly any thing that by nature is not God, they are concluded to be Idolaters. Yea, the words in the ſecond Commandment <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>thou ſhalt not bow down to them. nor ſhalt thou ſerve them.</hi> For [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] is properly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to ſerve.</hi> Yea, it may be obſerved that what the Papiſts do to the things that by nature are not God, is the ſame that our Saviour calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For they do <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fall down to</hi> and adore, or kiſs thoſe things before mentioned or ſome of them. Now when the Devil tempted Chriſt to do that to him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as it is in <hi>Luk.</hi> 4 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>falling down if thou wilt worſhip or proſtrate thy ſelf to or before me</hi> (which is what the Papiſts cannot deny but they give to the things above mentioned, they fall down to and kneel to or before them in their acts of religious worſhip) our Saviour repelling him with this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, plainly implies that, that that they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Divine worſhip</hi> to be given to God alone, is contained therein. That the <hi>Roman</hi> Church then are Idolaters is evident, for they worſhip and ſerve thoſe that are not God, nor allowed of God to be worſhipped, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly adored and ſerved by us. Nay, I may ſay too truly that God hath given them (as was ſaid of his dealing with <hi>Iſrael</hi> formerly for their neglects of God, and lifting up themſelves in pride againſt him) <hi>to worſhip the Hoſt of Heaven,</hi> Act. 7.42. only this difference there is, that the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> worſhipped the Viſible Hoſt, the Sun, Moon, and Stars, but theſe the Inviſible Hoſt, that is, the Saints, Angels, and Glorified Perſons; who as truly are the Hoſt of Heaven and not the God of Heaven, as the other was, though not ſo Viſible: and the worſhip of them as truly and really Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as the worſhip of the Viſible. Yea, they worſhip thoſe of whom there is leſs certainty that they are in Heaven, and ſo of whom there is leſs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty that they are any way beneficial to men in the leaſt, than there is of the Viſible Stars, as <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> St. <hi>Francis, Ignatius Loyola,</hi> and others, that probably might be no better Saints than <hi>Annas</hi> or <hi>Caiphas</hi> or ſome of our <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they give religious adoration to them that are not by nature God and to their Images too, is too groſs to be denyed; and what kind of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they give may be diſcerned in theſe inſuing inſtances that I ſhall here ſet down. Firſt in their Devotions to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> who I am ſure is not by nature God. To her they pray, and of her they aske ſuch grants, as only proper to God and Chriſt to give; and to her they aſcribe moſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly the ſame things that are aſcribed to God. As is to be ſeen in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48544:15"/>
inſuing inſtances among many others. Even St. <hi>Barnards</hi> devotions joining the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> with <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt are too full of this Idolatry, witneſs theſe following expreſſions.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Audi precor O plena gratiâ</l>
               <l>Peccatoris hujus ſuſpiria,</l>
               <l>Et pro tuâ miſericordiâ</l>
               <l>Deo meo me reconcilia,</l>
               <l>Mater bona.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And again
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Tibi Mater fac acceptabilem</l>
                  <l>Peccatoris hanc vocem flebilem,</l>
                  <l>Redde mihi Deum placabilem,</l>
                  <l>Ne ſe praeſtet inexorabilem</l>
                  <l>Quem offendi.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I engliſh it thus.
<q xml:lang="eng">
                  <l>Hear I pray O thou full of grace</l>
                  <l>This ſinners ſighs in piteous caſe,</l>
                  <l>And for thy mercy me again reſtore</l>
                  <l>Into favour with my God whom I adore,</l>
                  <l>O good Mother.</l>
                  <l>Make acceptable O Mother to thee</l>
                  <l>The wailing voice of the ſinful me,</l>
                  <l>Make God with me to be appeaſable,</l>
                  <l>That he may not be one inexorable,</l>
                  <l>Whom I have offended.</l>
               </q>
And yet he is modeſt in compariſon of ſome others who invoke Her by ſuch titles, as
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Reparatrix &amp; Salvatrix deſperantis animae,</l>
                  <l>Irroratrix &amp; Largitrix ſpiritualis gratiae.</l>
                  <l>The Repaireſs and the Savioreſs of Souls in deſpair,</l>
                  <l>The Bedewer with and Conferrer of graces that ſpiritual are.</l>
               </q>
Another accoſts her thus, <hi>peccatorum Conſolatrix, infirmorum Curatrix, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantium Revocatrix, Juſtorum Confirmatrix, deſolatorum ſpes &amp; auxiliatrix at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mea promptiſſima Adjutrix;</hi> that is, <hi>the female Comforter of ſinners, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the weak, caller back of thoſe that wander, Confirmer of the Juſt, the hope and helper of the deſolate,</hi> and ſaith the Devotioniſt, <hi>my moſt ready Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi> She is addreſſed to and prayed to alſo by the names of <hi>Excelſa Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Salvatrix ſaeculi, Regina Gentium,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the high Lady, the Savioureſs of the World, the Queen of the Nations.</hi> Which what are they but highly Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous expreſſions contrary to him that ſaid, <hi>thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> But beſides theſe, the very expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Scripture directed and attributed therein to God himſelf, are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to her, as may be ſeen in the <hi>Mary's</hi> Pſalter. So from the thirtieth (or according to our diviſion of them; the one and thirtieth) Pſalm they thus ſay to her. <hi>In te Domina ſperavi non confundar inaeternum, in gratiam tuam ſuſcipe me, inclina ad me aurem tuam, &amp; in maerore meo laetifica me. Tu es fortitudo mea, &amp; refugium meum, conſolatio mea, &amp; protectio mea; ad te clamavi cùm tribularetur c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r meum. In manus tuas Dom na commendo ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum meum, meam totam vitam, diem ultimum,</hi> that is, <hi>in thee O Lady have I put my truſt, let me not be confounded for ever, receive me into thy favour, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine ear to me, and in my mourning comfort me. Thou art my ſtrenght, my refuge, my conſolation and my protection; unto thee have I cryed when my heart
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48544:16"/>
was troubled. Into thy hands, O Lady, do I commend my ſpirit, my whole life, my laſt day.</hi> See here, is there not herein beſide the outward worſhip of the body, and the bodily act of invocation; a profeſſion of the moſt inward worſhip proper unto God, and moſt incommunicably to be reſerved unto him? Is there not here then groſs Idolatry and Blaſphemy, aſcribing to a creature that that is peculiar unto God. Of the like ſort is that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. <hi>Reſperge Domina cor meum dulcedine tuâ,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Beſprinkle my heart, O Lady, with thy ſweetneſs, make me to forget the miſeries of this life, ſtir up ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deſires in my ſoul, and inebriate, or make drunk, my mind with the joys of Paradiſe;</hi> and in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 46 <hi>aliàs</hi> the 47 thus, <hi>Omnes Gentes plaudite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, pſallite Jubilo Virginis glorioſae, quoniam ipſa eſt porta vitae, Janua ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis, &amp; Via noſtrae reconciliationis, ſpes paenitentium, ſolamen lugentium, pax beata cordium at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſalus,</hi> &amp;c. that is, <hi>ô clap your hands all ye Nations, ſing with a joyful voice to the glorious Virgin, becauſe She is the Gate of Life, the Door of ſalvation, and the Way of our Reconciliation, the Hope of thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, the Comfort of thoſe that mourn, the bleſſed peace and ſafety of hearts,</hi> &amp;c. with reference to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. it is alſo ſaid, <hi>Religioſi omnes honorate illam, quia ipſa est Adjutrix veſtra, &amp; ſpecialis Advocata. Eſto refrigerium noſtrum glorioſa Mater, quia Tues totius Religionis mirabile firmamentum,</hi> &amp;c. that is, <hi>All ye Religious men</hi> (or Cloyſterers) <hi>honour ye Her, becauſe She is your helper and ſpecial Advocate. Be thou our refreſhing, O glorious Mother of Chriſt, for thou art the marvelous foundation, or eſtabliſhment, of all Religion;</hi> upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20. <hi>Exaudi Domina, ſuccurre Animae cùm deſeruerit corpus ſuum, mitte Angelum in occurſum ejus per quem ab hoſtibus defendatur, ſentiat in paenis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frigerium tuum, &amp; concede locum inter Electos Dei,</hi> that is, <hi>Hear O Lady, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour my ſoul when it ſhall leave it's body, ſend an Angel to meet it, by whom it may be defended from it's enemies, let it feel thy refreſhing in the pains of</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, <hi>and give it a place among the Elect of God.</hi> And if this do not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſhew their guilt of Idolatry, I ſhall add a paſſage or two that will ſhew it with greater Blaſphemy, as when they ſay in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. <hi>Quia Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina humillima fuiſti, Verbum Increatum ex te carnem ſuſcipere coegiſti,</hi> that is, <hi>Becauſe thou, O Lady, waſt moſt humble, thou didſt conſtrain or compel the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Word to take fleſh of Thee,</hi> and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. <hi>Mater Dei, inclina vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Dei ſuper nos, coge illum peccatoribus miſereri. Mother of God, incline the countenance of God towards us, compel him to be merciful to ſinners.</hi> But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of this blaſphemous Idolatry with her. Yet all this and much more is to be found in that Pſalter of the bleſſed Virgin, ſaid to be made by their Seraphical Doctor St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> Biſhop of St. <hi>Albans,</hi> and one of the Cardinals of the holy (they might better have ſaid unholy) Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And their Primer made for their children after the uſe of <hi>Salisbury</hi> printed with a privilege according to the Kings and Queens Majeſties Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the reign of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> is of like complexion with that Pſalter, as is to be ſeen in <hi>Fox Martyro. volum.</hi> 3. <hi>pa.</hi> 273. witneſs theſe among other paſſages.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48544:16"/>Holy <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—So comfort us in our Deſolation,</l>
                  <l>That by thy prayer ond ſpecial Mediation</l>
                  <l>We may enjoy the reward of the Heavenly reign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
And again,
<q>
                  <l>The dolorous paſſion of Gods ſweet Mother</l>
                  <l>Bring us to the Bliſs of Almighty God the Father.</l>
               </q>
Again,
<q>
                  <l>O Thou meek Mother have mercy therefore</l>
                  <l>On Wretches for whom thou hadſt theſe pains all</l>
                  <l>Seeing thy Son that Vine-cluſter preſſed ſore,</l>
                  <l>And from the peſtilence of death eternal</l>
                  <l>Keep us by voiding the Fiend Infernal.</l>
                  <l>And join us with them that rewarded be</l>
                  <l>With eternal Life ſeeing the Deitie.</l>
               </q>
Nor only with Her do they commit this Idolatry, but with others alſo both Apoſtles and others of leſs worth, if not evil perſons, as may appear from the ſame Primer. Whence they teach their Children to be ſuch in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry betimes; teaching them not only to ſay, <hi>O Lord defend us always through the continual ſuccours of St.</hi> John <hi>Baptiſt;</hi> or with reference to the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul, Hear us mercifully, and grant that through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of them both, we may obtain the glory everlaſting;</hi> but alſo with reſpect to <hi>Thomas</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> murthered by occaſion of contempt againſt the then King, this is ſaid.</p>
            <q>
               <l>By the blood of <hi>Thomas</hi> which He for thee did ſpend,</l>
               <l>Make us (Chriſt) to climb whither <hi>Thomas</hi> did aſcend.</l>
            </q>
            <p>O Blaſphemy! And with reſpect to St. <hi>Nicholas, O God which haſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied bleſſed</hi> Nicholas, <hi>thy holy Biſhop, with innumerable miracles, grant we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee that by his merits and prayers, we may be delivered from the fire of Hell.</hi> To theſe I ſhall add ſome paſſages that Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> hath mentioned in his <hi>Antidote againſt Idolatry</hi> giving that in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that He hath therein ſet down in <hi>Latine</hi> only. Being pieces of Devotion publiquely read or ſung with <hi>Stentorian</hi> voices, as he phraſes it, in their very Churches; as to St. <hi>Coſmas</hi> and St. <hi>Damian</hi> two <hi>Quondam</hi> Phyſitians, they thus ſing.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>O Medici piiſſimi</l>
               <l>Qui meritis clariſſimi</l>
               <l>In Coelis refulgetis.</l>
               <l>A peſte, clade corporum</l>
               <l>Praeſervetis, &amp; operum</l>
               <l>Moribus nè langueamus.</l>
               <l>Nec moriamur ſpiritu,</l>
               <l>Sed Animae ab olitu</l>
               <l>Velociter ſurgamus,</l>
               <l>Et vivamus in gratiâ,</l>
               <l>Ad ſacra Caeli palatia</l>
               <l>Donec regrediamur.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>O Phyſitians moſt pious</l>
               <l>Who in merits being famous</l>
               <l>Brightly in the Heavens do ſhine.</l>
               <l>Keep us from peſtilence noiſom,</l>
               <l>The bodies death; and alſo from</l>
               <l>Bad manners, leſt in them we pine.</l>
               <l>Neither let us in ſpirit dy,</l>
               <l>But from Souls death haſtily</l>
               <l>Let us riſe again.</l>
               <l>And that we may live in grace</l>
               <l>Till to Heavens ſacred Palace</l>
               <l>We return to reign.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:48544:17"/>St. <hi>Francis</hi> they beſpeak to this purpoſe.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <hi>Sancte</hi> Franciſce <hi>properè veni. Pater accelera ad populum qui premitur &amp; teritur ſub onere, paleâ, luto, latere, &amp; ſepultos</hi> Aegyptio <hi>ſub ſabulo nos li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera carnis extincto vitio.</hi>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <hi>Holy</hi> Francis <hi>come apace, haſten Father to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple preſſed and worn out under their burthen, the Chaff, the Dirt, the Bricks. Free us that are buried under the</hi> Egyptian <hi>ſand</hi> (perhaps he may mean of Popiſh Superſtition) <hi>the corruption of the fleſh being extinguiſhed.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>St. <hi>Andrew</hi> they court thus.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Tam nos foveto languidos,</l>
               <l>Curám<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtrî ſuſcipe,</l>
               <l>Quò per Crucis victoriam</l>
               <l>Caeli petamus gratiam.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>Cheriſh us now who do languiſh,</l>
               <l>Take care of us in our anguiſh,</l>
               <l>That by the Croſs's victory</l>
               <l>We may get Heavens favour high.</l>
            </q>
            <p>St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> to this purpoſe.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Ergo piè nos exaudi</l>
               <l>Aſſiſtentes tuae laudi,</l>
               <l>Ne ſubdamur hoſtis fraudi</l>
               <l>Nobis fer auxilia.</l>
               <l>Nos ab omni malo ducas,</l>
               <l>Vitâ rectâ nos conducas,</l>
               <l>Poſt hanc vitam nos inducas</l>
               <l>Ad aeterna gaudia.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>Hear us therefore piouſly,</l>
               <l>Who aſſiſt thy praiſe duly.</l>
               <l>Againſt Sathans ſubtlety</l>
               <l>Help us left He us deſtroy.</l>
               <l>Let no evil us infect,</l>
               <l>In the right way us protect,</l>
               <l>After this life us direct,</l>
               <l>And bring to eternal joy.</l>
            </q>
            <p>St. <hi>Agnes</hi> they addreſs themſelves to after this ſort.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Ave <hi>Agnes</hi> Glorioſa</l>
               <l>Me in fide ſerves rectâ</l>
               <l>Dulcis Virgo &amp; dilecta</l>
               <l>Te exore precibus.</l>
               <l>Charitate da perfectâ</l>
               <l>Deum per quem es electa</l>
               <l>Colere pic omnibus.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>Hail <hi>Agnes</hi> who glorious art</l>
               <l>Fro' th' right faith let me not ſtart,</l>
               <l>O ſweet Virgin and dear Heart</l>
               <l>With my prayers I thee intreat.</l>
               <l>Grant to all men piouſly</l>
               <l>That with perfect charity</l>
               <l>They may worſhip God moſt high</l>
               <l>Whoſe choice hath made thee ſo great.</l>
            </q>
            <p>St. <hi>Bridget</hi> they Idolize thus.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>O <hi>Bregetta</hi> mater bona</l>
               <l>Dulcis Ductrix &amp; Matrona</l>
               <l>Nobis fer ſuffragia.</l>
               <l>Naufragantes in hoc mari</l>
               <l>Tuo ductu ſalutari</l>
               <l>Duc ad vitae bravia.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>O our good Mother <hi>Bridget</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our ſhe Guide and Matron ſweet</l>
               <l>Help us by thy ſuffrages,</l>
               <l>Who are ſhipwrackt in this Sea</l>
               <l>By thy conduct us ſafely</l>
               <l>Bring to life eternal wages.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:48544:17"/>But St. <hi>Catherine</hi> is more largely Deified of them after this manner.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Ave Virgo Dei digna</l>
               <l>Chriſto prece me conſigna,</l>
               <l>Audi preces, praeſta votum,</l>
               <l>Cor in bono fac immotum,</l>
               <l>Confer mihi cor contritum,</l>
               <l>Rege viſum &amp; auditum,</l>
               <l>Rege guſtum &amp; olfactum</l>
               <l>Virgo ſancta, rege tactum,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t in cunctis, te regente</l>
               <l>Vivam Deo purâ mente,</l>
               <l>Chriſtum pro me interpella</l>
               <l>Salva mortis de procellâ,</l>
               <l>Superare fac me mundum,</l>
               <l>Ne demergar in profundum.</l>
               <l>Ne me finas naufragari</l>
               <l>Per peccata in hoc Mari.</l>
               <l>Viſita tu me infirmum,</l>
               <l>Et in bonis fac me firmum</l>
               <l>Agoniſta Dei fortis</l>
               <l>Praeſtò ſis in horâ mortis,</l>
               <l>Decumbentem fove, leva,</l>
               <l>Et de morte ſolve ſaevâ</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t reſurgam novus homo</l>
               <l>Civis in Caeleſti domo.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>Worthy Maid of God I greet thee,</l>
               <l>By thy prayer for Chriſt bemeet me.</l>
               <l>Hear my prayers, perform my wiſh,</l>
               <l>In what's good my heart stabliſh.</l>
               <l>Grant to me a heart contrite,</l>
               <l>Rule my hearing and my ſight.</l>
               <l>Holy Maid, yea, taſt and ſmell,</l>
               <l>And my touch too order well.</l>
               <l>That in all, guided by thee,</l>
               <l>I may ſerve God with mind free.</l>
               <l>With Chriſt for me intercede,</l>
               <l>Save me from Deaths ſtormy dread.</l>
               <l>Make me overcome the World,</l>
               <l>Let me not to Hell be Hurl'd.</l>
               <l>Oh let me not ſhipwrackt be,</l>
               <l>By my Sins in this great Sea.</l>
               <l>Viſit thou me when Infirm</l>
               <l>And in goodneſs make me firm.</l>
               <l>Thou ſtrong wreſtler with the Lord,</l>
               <l>In deaths hour thy help afford.</l>
               <l>When I ſay Sick Nurſe and Chear me,</l>
               <l>And from cruel death loos'd bear me.</l>
               <l>That a new man I may riſe</l>
               <l>And may dwell above the Skies.</l>
            </q>
            <p>What they can deſire more of Chriſt himſelf than they expreſs in ſome of theſe, I know not, but yet beſides all this and much more of the like nature, they have alſo enacted in their Councils, both in the ſecond of <hi>Nice,</hi> and in that of <hi>Trent,</hi> that the very Images of Chriſt and of the Virgin, and of the Saints, are to be worſhiped, and that to with the ſame kind of worſhip, as Chriſt and his Saints are worſhiped with, point blank contrary to the ſecond commandment which they therefore, as is before ſaid, leave out of their Catechiſms, them they kiſs, and before them they uncover their Heads and proſtrate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to them they build Temples, and Altars, ſet up Candles, burn Incenſe and the like, pretending that that way they worſhip Chriſt and the Saints themſelves, juſt as the <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolaters uſe to do, of whom <hi>Origen</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Celſus,</hi> ſaith thus. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, we ſee ſometime men that are in high eſteem for Wiſdom and Divinity, bowing down themſelves to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48544:18"/>
Image of a corruptible Man, which they ſay they do for the honour of God; yea, and <hi>Celſus</hi> himſelf pleading for the worſhip of their Daemons, and for their Altars and Statues, hath this Plea, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, may not he that worſhips God lawfully enough, worſhip him that receives authority from him, as pretending to worſhip the great &amp; moſt high God, in worſhiping thoſe that were honoured by him. And again, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; He that honours and worſhips all them, what offence doth he to God (or how grieves he him) whoſe all are? how like to the Popiſh Doctors pleading for worſhipping their Saints and Images ſpake that Heathen; yea, and that by erecting Statues, or making Images to them, with which they commit their Idolatry as the Heathens did with theirs, they act like them alſo, may eaſily be ſeen with thoſe that will compare them: the Images of the Heathen uſed to be conſecrated as we hinted before; and what Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> quotes out of <hi>Minutius Faelix,</hi> jearing their Images, may well be applyed to them, when he ſaith, <hi>Ecce funditur, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricatur, ſcalpitur nondum Deus eſt. Ecce plumbatur, conſtruitur, erigitur, nec adhuc Deus eſt. Ecce ornatur, conſecratur, oratur; tunc poſtremo Deus eſt.</hi> That is, Io, the Image or Idol is Molten, Wrought, or Graven, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto it is no God, it is ſauldred, made up, and erected, neither yet is it a God, but when it is Adorned, Conſecrated, and Prayed to, then at length it becomes a God, ſuch kind of actions are done to the Popiſh Images to make them objects of Worſhip and Truſt; as thus (as the ſame Doctor tells us out of <hi>Chemnitius</hi>) they conſecrate the Image of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> 
               <q>Sanctifie, O God, this Image of the bleſſed Virgin, that it may aid and keep ſafe thy faithful people, that Thundrings and Lightnings, if they grow too terrible and dangerous, may be quickly expelled thereby; and that the Inundations of Rain, the commotions of Civil War, and devaſtations may be ſuppreſſed by its Preſence.</q> The Image of St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt thus, <q>Grant, O God, that all they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this Image with reverence, and pray before it, may be heard in whatſoever ſtraits they are in. Let this Image be the holy expulſion of Devils, the conciliating (or procurement) of the preſence and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Angels, the protection of the faithful, and that the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of this Saint may be very powerful in this place, who would not be drawn to adore ſuch an Image as they are perſwaded to be of ſo great advantage?</q> yea, but the Conſecration of Images, as in the Roman Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, publiſhed by two of their Popes ſince the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> runs higher, being thus, <q>Grant, O God, that whoſoever before this Image ſhall diligently and humbly upon his knees Worſhip and Honour thy only begotten Son, (or the B. Virgin, or what Saint the Image relates to) may obtain by his or her Merits or Interceſſion, grace in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48544:18"/>
life, and eternal glory hereafter.</q> So that the Saints here are made fellow Sharers with Chriſt or God in the diſpenſing grace and glory to, or procuring it for us; and their very Images are great advancers of their beneficence. Is not this too like the Heathens, who aſcribed to their Demons or middle Deities the handing to us the benefits we receive in all outward enjoyments, as is to be ſeen in what the abovenamed <hi>Celſus</hi> pleads for the worſhip of them; nay, do they not exceed their Pleas, in as much as they attribute alſo to their Interceſſions, the giving of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual grace and eternal glory: I ſhall not inſiſt upon all the Rites and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances practiſed and allowed in the ſaid Church to their Saints and their Images, which are ſuch as one of themſelves: <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> plainly confeſſes ſuch likeneſs to the Pagan Idolatries therein, that he ſaith, <hi>Non poteſt aliquod diſcrimen oſtendi, niſi quod nomina tantum &amp; ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulos mutaverint;</hi> that is, that there can no difference be ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe practiſes and the Pagans to their Idols, but only that they have changed their Names and Titles; for whereas the Learned Papiſts will ſay, that they are not ſo ſilly as to think theſe Images to be Gods, or to be able to help us, what ſay they therein, but what the Heathens alſo ſaid of their Altars and Images. <hi>Celſus</hi> ſaith, <q>If the Chriſtians condemn the Images or Statues of the Gods, becauſe that Stone, or Wood, or Braſs, or Gold, being wrought up by this or that Man into an Image, is not, nor cannot be God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> this is a ridiculous wiſdom, for who except he be a very fool or child, believes them to be Gods, but only things dedicated to, and the Images of the Gods:</q> but as they thought that their Demons or lower God, were to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by ſuch Statues and Images as repreſentations of them, or Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums to which their preſence and divine vertue were affixed, in honour of the moſt high God, as his Miniſters of good things to us, who were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be made propitious to men that they might convey good things from the great God to them, as is to be ſeen in the Pleas of the ſaid <hi>Celſus,</hi> ſo theſe think of the Saints and good Angels, and of their Images, and the anſwers that <hi>Origen</hi> gives to <hi>Celſus,</hi> ſhewing the reaſon why the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans made or worſhipped no ſuch Images, or worſhipped not God by them, will moſt of them be of the ſame force as to this practiſe of the Roman Church, as they were againſt that of the Heathen, and do clearly evidence that ſuch practiſes were diſallowed and rejected in his days by the then Chriſtian Church, though both the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and the Apoſtles were deceaſed long before, and were as much in glory, and in as good a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to help them then, as to help any now, and they needed as much then as ever, becauſe of their dreadful perſecutions that they then groaned under, for among other things, <hi>Origen</hi> tells <hi>Celſus,</hi> that the reaſon why the Jews and Chriſtians forbare ſuch worſhip of Idols and Images, was becauſe of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48544:19"/>
that in the Law. 'Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou Worſhip, and that thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me, thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf an Idol, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor the likeneſs of any thing in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, thou ſhalt not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them, nor ſerve them, and becauſe of that, thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve. With many other ſayings which ſaith he do ſo deter us from Temples, and Altars, and Images, that we ſhould rather chuſe to die, than to defile our Religion with unlawful matters. And afterward granting that God may be known, and his only begotten Son, and that thoſe whoever they be that are honoured of God with the title of Gods, or are made partakers of the Deitie, are different from the Gods of the Nations which are Devils. Yet he adds, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that it is impoſſible for one to know God, and to pray to Images;</hi> and that it is not only a fooliſh thing to worſhip and pray to Images, but alſo to pretend or appear to do ſo, complying with the multitude, as certain of the Philoſophers did uſe to do. Yea, &amp; that they took heed with all care not to honour Images, leſt by any means they ſhould give occaſion of believing that they were others Gods, and often aſſerts that <q>the Chriſtians refuſed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to worſhip any thing elſe than the God over all, and his Word, the firſt begotten of every creature,</hi> and that they did, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>worſhip the God over all by his Son, who only brings us to him, without Schiſm, Separation or diviſion.</hi>
               </q> There was then no extending the acts of worſhip beyond God, and his bleſſed Word or Son; nor any belief entertained in the Church of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or any of the deceaſed Apoſtles, Angels, or other Saints, having any share committed to them in the office of Mediator, for bringing the worship of the worshippers unto God; or for imparting his grace unto them. No, theſe were then accounted ſtrange and corrupt notions, if any ſuch were as yet crept into any hearts, and they are evident Adulteries from the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and loyalty or the ſimplicity of faith that we owe to God in and by Chriſt Jeſus. The proper Apoſtacy of the laſt times foretold by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. as Reverend Mr. <hi>MEDE</hi> hath learnedly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in his Treatiſe upon that Scripture. Wherein he that will may ſee this argument excellently handled, and amongſt other things, a large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation out of the eight Book of <hi>Theodoret, de curandis Graecorum affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus,</hi> of the Chriſtians having then taken in the Saints and Martyrs into the place of the Heathen Daemons, as among other paſſages, theſe words teſtifie, <q>Eorum qui paſſim Dii ferebantur memoriam è mente hominum Martyres aboleverint. Suos mortuos dominus Deus noſter in Templo pro diis veſtris, i. e. daemonibus iri duxit— Pro-Jovis liberi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Patris ſolemnitatibus Petro, Paulo, Thomae, Sergio, aliiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Sanctis Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyribus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48544:19"/>
ſolennitates epulo populari peraguntur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>that is, the Martyrs have aboliſhed the memory of thoſe that were commonly accounted Gods. Our Lord God would have his dead brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Temples inſtead of your Gods, that is, the Devils, inſtead of the Feaſts of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the people now keep Feaſts to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> to <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Sergius, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And what the Papiſts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their doing all the ſame things that we Proteſtants do, but they do more alſo, is but all one in this matter, as if a Woman ſhould ſay that ſhe doth all things to her Husband that another honeſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth to hers, but ſhe doth this more, that whereas the other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Woman yields her Body to her Husband only, and admits no other man into her Bed beſides, ſhe out of reſpect to her Husband, admits him and his Servants, and familiar Friends alſo. And as a wiſe Husband would ſcarce think that a good honour given or done to him by his Wife, no more will God take ſuch adulterous embraces of the Saints, and their Images, and the like, as a good honouring of him, its like alſo as if the falſe Apoſtles and their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers ſhould have pleaded againſt the true Apoſtles, and theirs that they did the ſame things with them, but they exceeded them, and did more; for they not only Baptized into the Name of Chriſt, but Circumciſed too, and were Circumciſed after the manner of <hi>Moſes;</hi> nor did they only celebrate the Lords Supper, but alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the dayes and times appointed in the Law; and ſurely there was more colour for their ſo pleading, than for theſe mens, for they had ſomething formerly of Gods appointment to ſhew for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but theſe have nothing at all but many prohibitions there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt to produce. Nothing ſaid I? Yes, I remember the Plea of a Jeſuite for the Picture of Chriſt (though nothing for worſhip to be given it, nor for worſhiping the Saints and their Images) from the Apoſtles ſaying to the <hi>Galathians</hi> that they were Fools to turn to <hi>Moſes</hi> law when Chriſt Jeſus had been ſet forth and evidently cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed among them, the word ſaith he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, was Pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and therefore they had the Picture of Chriſt drawn before their Eyes, even of Chriſt Crucifyed; ſurely the Jeſuits was hard put to it for a proof that he was fain to fetch one from that word, by the ſame way he might prove that the Prophets of old were Painters and Image makers, becauſe its ſaid in <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo it ſhould be tranſlated whatſoever things were Pictured aforetime, were Pictured for our Inſtruction, &amp; he might have found the Pictures of other men beſides Chriſt, though not of the Saints, unleſs ſuch ſaints as ſome of them of the Roman Church may be, for <hi>Jude</hi> tells us of ſome that were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſhall we read, Pictured out unto this Condemnation? <hi>Jude</hi> 4. <hi>ungodly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48544:20"/>
Men.</hi> Surely the Jeſuit was either a man of little judgment, or which is rather to be judged of a profligate conſcience that mattered not with what colours to paint over his matters, or elſe he would have waved ſuch a proof for ſo bad a purpoſe, and have remembred that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and their fellow Labourers whither they did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ingrave or pourtray, yet it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not in Tables of Stone, as the Romiſh Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturers work but in the fleſhly Tables of the heart, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not with Ink or ſuch like Paint, but with the Spirit of God, as the Apoſtle writes in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. and with ſuch a manner of drawing, I ſuppoſe their Picture makers have little or no acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor indeed would it have deſerved the title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Fooliſh <hi>Galathians;</hi> had the falſe Apoſtles only drawn them from a Chriſt Crucifyed as repreſented in an externally viſible Picture or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of him, wherein nothing but his body and fleſh, or rather the external lineaments, proportion and complexion of it, could be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, and ſo the ſhape of a man Crucifyed; nothing of his Deity and inward Virtue, as they deſerved for being drawn from him, as Painted forth by the Spirit in the Goſpel, to the eyes of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, as the Son of God; and ſo as God manifeſted in the fleſh, and baring our Sins in his Body on the Tree, and there through geting the victory over Sin, and death, and the Divel, which no Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in matters of Stone or other Metals could draw to the Life, the other might rather offend them and give the falſe Apoſtles ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage againſt believing on him, than perſwade to conſtancy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, there being nothing but a Crucifyed man repreſented to them therein.</p>
            <p>But I have been tedious in making good this charge; but therein I ſuppoſe I have abundantly diſcovered the truth thereof, that <hi>Rome</hi> Papal is as arrant a Whore as <hi>Rome</hi> Pagan was; nay, in one reſpect far greater and worſe, for in thoſe times ſhe was not eſpouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Chriſt as ſuch, &amp; therefore was not charged then as commiting adultery from him, or breaking Wedlock as now, that having been the Catholick Church, and her Faith that that was preached in the whole World, and ſhe a famous Mother without it, yet ſhe hath played the Harlot from him (like <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.15.) as being corrupted from the ſimplicity in him to ſwarve ſo much from her loyalty to him and admit a multitude into the Bed of love beſides him, yea, the Kings of the Earth alſo, with whom ſhe hath truckt for their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and riches, crowns and ſcepters, accommodating her ſelf to their wills, that ſhe might lift up her ſelf by them, and get her will on them, as in the famous Story of her Biſhop <hi>Boniface,</hi> chaffering with <hi>Phocas,</hi> who having Murthered his own Maſter <hi>Mauritius,</hi> and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48544:20"/>
his Children, was owned as Emperour in his ſtead by the ſaid <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface,</hi> that he might (as he was) be made and declared by him to be the Univerſal Biſhop over all the Churches in Chriſtendom, upon a fond pretence never before thought on (its likely) that becauſe Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> that he would give him the keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, therefore the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> (however unlike to St. <hi>Peter</hi>) and without any delegation of them by him in any of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles or other ways of conveyance of them to them) muſt rule over all the Church in all after ages. A notable reward of <hi>Romes</hi> Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with that Murtherer, but that may lead me to another particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar charge agreeable alſo with the character given her (which alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares her to be the <hi>Babilon</hi> ſpoken of) by the holy ghoſt in the book of the <hi>Revelations, viz.</hi> That</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not only a Whore and the great Whore, but a Bloody Whore too, elſe ſhe ſhould not be that <hi>Babilon,</hi> for St. <hi>John</hi> was ſhewed that ſo ſhe would be, for he ſaw her drunk with the Blood of the Saints, and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus, to his great admiration and amazement, and that in her was found the blood of the Prophets and of Saints, and of all that were Slain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.6. and 18.24. and indeed it may be doubted whither ſhe ſlew more in her Pagan ſtate, to raiſe and maintain her imperial dignity among and over the nations of the World, as to bodily ſlaughters in all her Wars and Battels, or more Souls ſpritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in raiſing her ſelf to, and maintain her ſelf in her Papal Empire. And again, whither ſhe made more Martyrs of Jeſus, or ſlew more in their bodys for confeſſing him to be the Son of God in her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan ſtate; or for confeſſing and cleaving to the ſimplicity and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of the Goſpel againſt her ſpiritual fornications from, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of it in her Papal ſtate, but in both ſtates and in both ways its certain that ſhe hath been and is notoriouſly guilty of Blood and Murther, for if no Idolater hath any part in the Kingdom of God and Chriſt, and they that depart from the ſimplicity of the faith to adulterate it with other mixtures, are thereby aboliſhed from Chriſt, as the Apoſtle ſaith of thoſe that were Circumciſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 2, 3, 4, 19, 20.21. how ſhall not thoſe Millions of Souls which ſhe leads in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe Sins, as is above ſhewed, be ruined by her! and as for Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and Martyring the bodys of thoſe that cleave to the Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the truth, and witneſs againſt her corruptions, what multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes hath ſhe Maſſacred and murthered! witneſs the <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> (as they call them) in <hi>France,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Vallies</hi> of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> &amp;c. beſides the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes burnt at ſtakes and otherwiſe Martyred, in <hi>England, Holland, Spain, Italy, Germany,</hi> and in almoſt all Countries, ſo that what the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48544:21"/>
Prophets teſtify of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> playing the Whore from the Lord, is too truely applicable to this Papal Babilon, for as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was a bloody City, the City that ſhed blood in the midſt of it, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.2, 3. an Imperious Whoriſh Woman that ſlew Gods Children, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was to be judged as Women that break Wedlock and ſhed Blood are judged, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20, 21, 30, 38. in her skirts was found the blood of the Souls of the poor innocents, and yet ſo impudently hardned as to deny her guiltyneſs, and plead I am Innocent, I have not ſinned, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.34.35. <hi>I am rich, I have found me out ſubſtance, in all my labours they ſhall find no Iniquity in me, that were ſin, Hoſ.</hi> 12.8. an Infallible Church. Juſt ſo is it with Rome, and as her Blood was, ſo this Churches is in the midſt of her; She ſet, <hi>and this ſets it upon the top of a Rock, in the view of all Men, ſhe poured it not upon the ground to cover it with duſt, Ezek.</hi> 24.7. no ſurely, ſhe was not aſhamed of all her Blood and cruelty, though her ſword devoured her Prophets, and ſlew the juſt, doubtleſs ſhe ſaid and juſtifyed it by her falſe prophets, that they were all mad men and falſe prophets whom ſhe ſlew, Hereticks and Factious perſons that would charge her with Idolatry and Whoredom from God, for worſhiping him upon Hills and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and under green Trees, and ſome <hi>Baalim</hi> or matters with him, and therefore ſhe endeavoured not to hide her murtherous doings. Juſt ſo this Church of Rome, a Bloody Harlot, both in reſpect of Soul Murther, and Body Murther in all her territories, yet ſhe will ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify her ſelf by her Panders, her Prieſts and Jeſuits, that ſhe is Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, an infallible Church, under the conduct of an infallible Guide, her Biſhop, that will not fail to lead her Members and Children to Hell and deſtruction. She will not yield that ſhe commits Adultery from Chriſt, or that Saint worſhip, or Image Worſhip, or Hoſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or any Idolatrous or falſe worſhips, nor is ſhe aſhamed of thoſe Bloody facts ſhe hath done, ſhe ſets her Blood on a Rock, powers it not in the Duſt to cover it, but juſtifies all, yea, glories in and gives publick thanks for her rare atchievments, and honours thoſe that are actors in them, though they Murther Kings, endeavour to blow up Parliaments, fire Citys. The more miſchief they do in her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, the more meritorious; ſhe is Innocent, and not grieved, except it be becauſe ſhe can have her will no more, Maſſacre Hereticks no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: but God will give her blood in his due time to drink according to all her Idolatries againſt himſelf, and Son, and Murthers done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Souls of Men, and upon the Bodys of his ſaints and holy ones, as is predicted in the Revelations, <hi>He alſo will ſet her blood upon the Top of a Rock, that it ſhould not be covered, therefore, thus ſaith the Lord God, woe to the Bloody City, I will even make the Pile for Fire great,</hi> ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.8.9. Oh, who that looks upon her in the light of Gods teſtimony,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48544:21"/>
can be deluded with her fair pretences, or reguard her devices, but will rather acknowledge the truth of what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> long ſince in his Epiſtle to that Church predicted would befal her, upon the courſe ſhe hath ſince taken. For (to interpoſe by the way a third conſideration.)</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Apoſtle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.21, 22, 23. implyed or ſuppoſed her Fallible, contrary to her own boaſt of her ſelf, and ſhews the way how ſhe might come to fall, warning her of it. And indeed that way ſhe is fallen foully, as therein was foreſhewed together with what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal her further. Let us view his words, they are thus, <hi>Thou standeſt by faith, be not high minded, but fear. For if God ſpared not the natural Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, take heed leſt he alſo ſpare not thee (or neither in any wiſe will he ſpare thee) Behold therefore the ſeverity and goodneſs of God, on them that fell, ſeverity, but towards thee, goodneſs, if thou continue in his goodneſs, otherwiſe thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhalt be cut off.</hi> Now, who did the Apoſtle there ſpeak and write to? Was it not to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (who were then Saints, but now all her Saints are dead and glorified Perſons, no Saints living now in <hi>Rome,</hi> none that will own that name, or be acknowledged to be ſuch. A ſign they are fallen, for then the living members of it were Saints, but now there are no Saints in her, but they that are long ſince gone, but it was the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that he ſpeaks to) and ſo it is as if he had ſaid, Thou Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtandeſt by faith, that is, by an obedient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on God and Chriſt, in an hearty belief of his Goſpel, cleaving to him, and his inſtructions, and commands, and holding faſt the faith as delivered to thee. Implying, that otherwiſe ſhe is Fallible, and might and would fall, and therefore it concerned them to take heed of high-mindedneſs, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, mind not high things, have no high conceits of thy ſelf; thou Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if thou wouldſt not fall, but keep thy ſtanding, be not high minded, but fear. As implying, that if ſhe grew high minded, and were puffed up, ſhe would fall. For indeed <hi>Pride goeth before deſtruction, and a haughty mind before a fall,</hi> Prov. 16.18. where Pride and High-mindedneſs then are found, and fear is laid aſide, there a fall certainly and inevitably follows, even as fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from God and Chriſt as to a hearty dependance on him, and cloſe cleaving to him, and to his will and directions in which they ſhould be preſerved, as that was the way the Branches came to be broken off, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> to fall by her iniquity. Jeſurun <hi>waxed fat and kicked, ſhe wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fat, grew thick, and was covered with fatneſs. Then he forſook God that made him, and lightly eſteemed the God of his ſalvation; of the Rock that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed him he was unmindful, and forgot God that formed him, and moved him to jealouſy with ſtrange Gods, and ſacrificed to Daemons,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 32.15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>According to their paſture ſo were they filled, and their heart was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted; therefore they have forgotten me, and ſacrificed to them that were not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48544:22"/>
Gods, to new Gods,</hi> &amp;c. Hoſ. 13.6. with Deut. 32.17. They boaſted that they were <hi>Abrahams Seed,</hi> and ſo in covenant with God, that it was impoſſible for them to be cut off, and to be rejected; they muſt alwayes be owned of him, as is implyed of them in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.32, 33. An Infallible Church, not minding that as God ſaid to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> He could have cut them all off generally with his judgments, and out of ſome one perſon of them, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> he could have performed his promiſe to <hi>Abraham, Exod.</hi> 32.10. raiſed up a ſeed to him, <hi>that ſhould be as the Stars for multitude,</hi> yea, <hi>out of ſtones,</hi> as the Baptiſt ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.9. This High-mindedneſs and Pride leading them to boaſt, as ſo in covenant with God, and ſo to boaſt of God, as ſo ingaged to them, that they could not miſcarry; and ſo of their Law and skill in it, and of their Temple and the like, led them into careleſneſs and fearleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and imboldened them to turn aſide from Gods teſtimonies, and hardened them againſt the Calls given them by the Prophets, and by the Baptiſt, and by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to repentance. And ſo they became blind with a conceit of their Infallibility or impoſſibility of falling, and ſo through unbelief they were broken off, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.17, 18, 19. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.4. and 23.14, 16, 17. And of this therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was warned that ſhe might have continued in Gods goodneſs, and it was poſitively threatned to her that otherwiſe ſhe alſo ſhould be cut off. But hath ſhe taken warning, verily no? If there be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of people in the World that are proud and high-minded, it hath been and are they. And that's another charge, That</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a proud Imperious Harlot, for hath ſhe not lifted up her ſelf (in her Heads at leaſt) above all that is cal'd God or worſhipped, not only above Kings and Emperors, as is moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious (as much above them as the Sun is greater than the Moon, as one of them expreſſed himſelf) but even above God and Chriſt, alſo in daring to diſpenſe with his Laws and Precepts, and to ſet up their Decrees againſt them with a <hi>non obſtante,</hi> or notwithſtanding that God or Chriſt otherwiſe ordered or commanded. As in leaving out the ſecond Commandment, and worſhipping, and bowing down to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, contrary thereto; denying the Cup to the people in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nay, doth ſhe not boaſt that her Prieſts can make God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of a piece of bread or wafer? And is not that a wondrous unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd height of Arrogancy to preſume to do ſo, and a ſetting her above all that's called God or worſhiped? For let reaſon or wiſe men judge. If as one ſaid, <hi>majus eſt Regem facere quàm regem eſſe,</hi> it's a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thing to make a King than to be one; muſt it not needs be a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er power to make a God than to be a God? If therefore they can make Almighty God, as they believe they do, Chriſt very God and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man. Do they not ſet themſelves above him, and have it in their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48544:22"/>
power to make him or not; the effect therein, as they ſay, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Prieſt's intentions, ſo as if he intend not to tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Bread, it is not made into a God by him, though he ſay the words that make him. And if the ordinary Prieſts have ſuch power, how great is his height that is the Head and King of them? But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, have they not arrogated to themſelves the Title of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and the promiſes made to the Church, as ſolely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them? Though they have far leſs to ſhew for any promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to them more than to any other Church, than the <hi>Jews</hi> had to ſhew that the promiſes made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed pertained to them. Nor have they minded, that as God could have deſtroyed the <hi>Jews</hi> as to the generality of them, and yet have raiſed up Seed to <hi>Abraham</hi> to perform his promiſes unto. So God can leave and cut off the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet perform his promiſe of a Church to be given and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved continually unto Chriſt; and to ſecure the Church built upon Chriſt, and humbly and ſincerely cleaving to him, againſt the gates of Hell. Chriſts ſaying to <hi>Peter, Tu es</hi> Petrus, <hi>&amp; ſuper hanc petram aedifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Eccleſiam meam, &amp; tibi dabo claves regni Coelorum,</hi> that is, <hi>Thou art</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>and upon this Rock will I build my Church, and to thee will I give the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. are not half ſo colourable a plea for the Popes and the Church of <hi>Romes</hi> pretences, as Gods ſaying to <hi>Abraham</hi> that he would be his God, and the God of his Seed after him through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their generations, was for the <hi>Jews</hi> conceit, that they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be broken off by him. For they cannot ſhew that <hi>Peter</hi> only had the Keys of the Kingdom, ſeeing all the other Apoſtles had the ſame power of binding and looſing mens ſins as he; as the Primitive Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors alſo acknowledged, and as is evident in <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.22, 23. nor that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was either the only or the whole Church built upon the Rock, which was not <hi>Peter,</hi> but Chriſt; unleſs St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a falſe Preacher in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. and 10.4. Nor can they find in Chriſt's grant to St. <hi>Peter</hi> any ſuch clauſe, as to thee will I give them, and to thy Succeſſors at <hi>Rome</hi> in all ages and generations, as we find to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed after him the promiſes made. But this alſo is another evidence of their pride and arrogancy, exalting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above Chriſt and God, that they dare preſume to inlarge his promiſes, and put in clauſes of their own head into his Will and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as well as alter and lay by his Commandments. A bold Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious Harlot. It would be accounted a very preſumptuous deed in a Wife to add ſuch a clauſe into a mans Teſtament; for as the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>If it be but a mans Covenant or Teſtament, yet if it be confirmed, no man addeth thereto,</hi> as they make bold to do to his who is God, <hi>Gall.</hi> 3.15. But ſhould we grant beyond any evidence or proof, that St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:48544:23"/>
left his Keys to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> ſucceſſively; yet ſeeing Pope <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the ſecond in his expedition againſt the <hi>French,</hi> ſome ages ſince threw them into the River <hi>Tyber,</hi> ſaying, becauſe St. <hi>Peters</hi> Keys would not do his work, he would betake him to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Sword: how doth it appear that he and his Succeſſors did not thereby looſe them forever? When did Chriſt make any new ones, and give to him, or thoſe that ſuceeded him? But herein alſo her exceſſive pride appears, in that her Biſhops challenge both St. <hi>Peters</hi> Keys, and St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Sword; nay, both Swords, both the Civil and Sacred, or Eccleſiaſtical (for I think the truly Spiritual they care not much for, at leaſt as to any true &amp; right uſe thereof) that is, they chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge Dominion in Temporal matters, &amp; uſurp upon the rights of Kings &amp; Princes, and to exerciſe a power in diſpoſing of Thrones and Scepters, and making Civil Wars, as well as to rule over all Nations in Church matters. Never was there any Chuch or company of People in the World ranting it ſo highly, and carrying it ſo aloft, as this Church and her Biſhops have done ever ſince they obtained of <hi>Phocas</hi> the high Honour he conferred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, to make them an amends for approving him in the Murther of his Maſter, in ſetling the dignity of Emperor upon him; and this ſuits well with the deſcription of my ſtory of <hi>Babilon</hi> too in the <hi>Revelations;</hi> where ſhe is repreſented as <hi>mounted upon a Stately Beaſt with ſeven Heads and ten Horns,</hi> as being both exalted and ſupported therein by, and yet ruling and ordering the Imperial Power, <hi>Sitting upon many Waters,</hi> that is, ruling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver many Nations, People, and Languages, gallantly deckt, and making all Nations drunk of the Cup of her Fornications; glorifying her ſelf in ſtead of God and Chriſt) and ſaying, I ſit as a Queen (as the Lambs wife, the Catholique Church, to whom all in all eſtates owe honour and ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>and am no Widdow</hi> (Infallible, not forſaken of Chriſt, and ſo) <hi>ſhall ſee no ſorrow; the City that ruleth over the Kings of the Earth,</hi> Revel. 17.1, 2, 3, 4, 18. and 18.7. Surely if pride go before deſtruction, and a haughty mind before a fall, then it cannot be but ſo proud and <hi>Luciferian</hi> a Church muſt needs fall too. If the Angel of the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> becauſe of his high boaſtings, that he was rich and increaſed with goods, growing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by lukewarm, was threatned to be ſpewed out of Chriſts mouth, and what was ſaid to him, was ſaid to the Churches by the ſpirit, as imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that any of them falling into the like temper, muſt be ſo dealt with, except they repented, how can it be, but that this Church hath long ſince met with that doome, ſeeing ſhee for a long time, hath been far more Proud and Highminded, than that Angel was, and no leſs lukewarm or indifferent for the honour of Chriſt, ſo ſhe may be but the Queen and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, eſpecially alſo ſeeing ſhe obſtructs the way againſt her repentance; by pleading ſhe is Infallible, and ſo needs no repentance: juſtifying by her Prieſts and Jeſuits her ſelf and her practices in all theſe vile and filthy miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, doing therein (as was noted before) like <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of old,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48544:23"/>
that would not acknowledge that ſhe had tranſgreſſed, and ſcattered her ways to ſtrangers, and had not obeyed Gods voice, but would againſt the moſt notorious and palpable evidences of her guilt, yet ſay ſhe was not pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, ſhe had not gone after <hi>Baalim,</hi> or other Lords and Maſters beſides her own proper God. Even ſo it is with this proud imperious Chuch, ſhe will lift up her ſelf againſt all charges, and will not own her ſelf guilty of Idolatry, or corrupt in her faith &amp; worſhip; but will boaſt of her being the Church, the Catholique Church the Infallible Church &amp; talk of her Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Univerſality, Unity, &amp; challenge all the Apoſtles, Prophets, Martyrs Confeſſors, Ancient Doctors, Councels, to be hers: when indeed &amp; in truth in their true and genuine Doctrines, the Apoſtles, Prophets, Primitive Doctors and Councels, all condemn her. It is true ſhe may in many things boaſt of her Antiquity, and ſo may the Devil and his Followers who alſo can ſhew as great an Univerſality and Unity; for ſhould he be <hi>divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf</hi> (as our Saviour ſaith) <hi>his kingdom could not ſtand,</hi> Luk. 11.18. but, <hi>non omne quod antiquum eſt, verum eſt, ſed quod primum; not all that is ancient</hi> (though of great latitude and extent, and at unity with it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) <hi>but that that is the firſt, that is true and right.</hi> So God was the firſt and before the Devil, and his truth was before error and falshood, and the Articles of the Chriſtian faith were long before any noyſe was heard of the Popes Supremacy, or being Chriſts Vicar, or of his having derived the Keys, or the Power over the whole Church from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Purgatory, or Tranſubſtantiation, or their Merit of our works, or of Works of Super-errogation, or of the Cup being denyed to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or of the Latine Service or Prayers injoyned in an unknown Tongue, or of the Worship of Images, or Invocation of the Saints, or of whatever elſe is properly Roman, as diſtinguished from all other Profeſſors of the Chriſtian Religion. Which are ſo many groſs and horrid Errors into which she is fallen and from the charge of guilt wherein she cannot clear her ſelf; <hi>But though ſhe waſh her with Nitre, and take much Sop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, yet they are and will be marked before the Lord,</hi> as He ſaid ſometime to <hi>Jeruſalem, Jer.</hi> 2.22. and therefore alſo being ſo fowly fallen into Error and Iniquity, and not confeſſing and repenting, but juſtifying her ſelf, and ſaying, in deſpite of all the moſt evident convictions, that she is innocent; it cannot be but that what God threatned to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> will alſo be her portion; and that in a far more dreadful and ſevere manner, that is, that he will plead with her, and execute upon her all the terrible Judgment written in <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. So as she shall be thrown down into the Pit of deſtruction with great vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence even by the mighty hand of God, ſo as she shall be found no more at all; becauſe she inſtead of owning her guilt, and repenting of her Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Blood-shed, Pride, and all her other Enormities ſaith she is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: and her lying falſe Prophets dawb her up with their untempered Mortar, and ſee for her vain and foolish things, inſtead of diſcovering her
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48544:24"/>
iniquity to turn away her miſery. Yea, they ſee for her (as <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> falſe Prophets did for her) <hi>falſe buthens and cauſes of baniſhment of her, and all that cleave to her for ever from Gods preſence,</hi> Jer. 2.32. Lam. 2.14. Rev. 18.2. and she loves to have it ſo. For if any be convinced of her Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and proteſt againſt them, being converted from them, they ſeek if poſſible to murther and deſtroy them. As many have proved, and as Mr. <hi>Anthony Aegan</hi> tells us they have endeavoured diverſe ways to do to him, ſince his converſion from them, and proteſts againſt them, and endeavours to reclaim any of them. But the time is haſtening, when as she is fallen into the Dregs of Impiety, Error, and Apoſtacy, from her Primitive Faith and Worship in its purity; multiplying as many falſe Objects of worship, as ever Pagan <hi>Rome</hi> did with her <hi>Pantheon;</hi> ſo she muſt becauſe of her ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy and impenitency fall under Gods moſt ſevere and terrible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments forethreatned: that as she is become a very Sink of ſin and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, ſpiritual and corporal, ſo she may ſink into an Abyſs of woe and miſery eternal.</p>
            <p n="10">10. In all that I have ſaid and ſhewed, it appears that ſhe is alſo a falſe Church, or a lying Harlot, ſo far is ſhe from being Infallible, though I ſhall evince it ſtill further in ſpeaking ſomething to what ſhe pretends very much as an undeniable proof of her being the true Church at leaſt. Namely the multitude of her Miracles wherewith She endeavours to eſtabliſh all other her Falſe doctrines and practiſes, as her doctrine of Images and Saint Worſhip, her doctrine of Purgatory, and of Tranſubſtantiation, and what not almoſt She pleads Miracles for confirmation of, and this being added to her other Notes of her Antiquity, Univerſality, and Unity, make her to glitter mainly in the eye of many ſimple people, concerning which, I may ſhew her to be a falſe lying Church too in a two fold reſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In her pretending ſuch things as She calls Miracles, the ſignes and ſtrange wonders that ſhe boaſts of to be a good and undoubted note of a true Church owned of God, and that the doctrines which they tend to confirm are true; that this is falſe, we have manifold evidences. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord himſelf by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuppoſeth the contrary, when he ſaith, If there be a Prophet or a dreamer of dreams, and he give thee a ſign or a wonder, and that ſign, or that wonder come to paſs that he foretold of, ſaying, let us go after other Gods,— thou ſhalt not hearken to the words that Prophet, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. Such ſigns and wonders then are no true Note, or ſufficient evidence of the rightneſs of a perſon, or of a people, that doth or liſtens to them that do them, or of the doctrines confirmed by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> alſo tells us, that the man of ſin, that wicked one, whoſe coming is after the manner of Sathan, ſhall come with power and ſigns, and lying wonders, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wonders of falſhood, partly ſo called, becauſe done to confirm falſhoods, and he ſhall alſo have a great
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48544:24"/>
number of followers after him, even the generality of thoſe that have not received the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And our Saviour himſelf warning his Diſciples of the falſe Chriſts, and the falſe Prophets, (which have been creeping into the world, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Churches ever ſince the Apoſtles time, ſuch their Antiquity) that ſhould ſhew great ſigns and wonders, ſo as to deceive, if poſſible, the very Elect; who being the feweſt, its moſt rational to ſuppoſe, that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of thoſe that have not Elect, or choſen out of the world, are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by them; and ſo that there is a great over-ſpreading univerſality of them alſo, and they at unity as to their following theſe Impoſtors and deceivers of them, by their great ſigns and wonders, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.24, 25.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And in <hi>Revelations</hi> 13. we read of a Beaſt after whom the whole world wonders (ſo great the univerſality of his power, and of them that approve him unanimouſly) before whom a ſecond Beaſt ſhall do, or doth ſo great ſigns, and wonders, and miracles as to cauſe fire to come down from Heaven in the ſight of the Beaſt, and in the ſight of Men; that is, he ſhall do ſuch things in the ſight or judgment of men, as do as clearly in their judgments teſtifie Gods approvement of him in what he propounds to them, as he did <hi>Elijah,</hi> when he cauſed Fire to deſcend from Heaven, and conſume his Sacrifice offered to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and yet he is a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet for all that, and his Image that he ſets up to be worſhipped, and all the Marks and Characters that he cauſeth people to take, by which they may be known to be the Beaſt worſhippers, and the worſhippers of his Image, it is certain are naught, and moſt diſpleaſing to God; who therefore threatens the worſhippers and receivers thereof with moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful puniſhments, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9, 10, 11. and yet he by theſe Miracles, and other exerciſes of his power, cauſes them that dwell on the Earth to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thereto; yea all, both ſmall and great, rich and poor, to give ſome way or other an acknowledgment of it, ſuch their univerſality and unity therein. And its of great Antiquity, if the judgment of the moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and judicious Expoſitors may be taken, who judge that the 42. months, or 1260 days of the continance of that Worſhip, ſignifies one thouſand two hundred and ſixty years, a day for a year, as is ſometimes the reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Prophets, as in <hi>Num.</hi> 14.34. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.12, 13, 14, 15, 16. ſo that this worſhip hath been in the world, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> hath learnedly hinted in his Apoſtacy of the laſt times ſince between the Fifth and Sixt Century.</p>
            <p n="5">5. How early in the world began the Pagan Idolatry! how far and near did it ſpread it ſelf, and that for many ages and generations, the Nations of the world unanimouſly agreeing therein; for though its true that they worſhipped diverſe Gods, and had in ſeveral places different rites and ways of worſhipping, yet they might for all that be ſaid to have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48544:25"/>
as great an unity and unanimity in their worſhip, as the Papiſts have, ſeeing they alſo worſhip divers Saints, and ſome of them are more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly addicted to one Saint, and ſome to another, and obſerve divers aind different Orders in their different Devotions: ſome being of the Order of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> ſome of <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> ſome Votaries to one Saint, and ſome to another. Now the Pagans alſo had their Signs and Wonders to confirm them in their Religion, by the operation and working of Sathan, witneſs what <hi>Celſus</hi> aforementioned writes of them, as it is recited by <hi>Origen</hi> to this purpoſe, <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. what ſhould I reckon up how many things partly the Prophets and Prophetiſſes (namely of the Pagans) partly other perſons,<note place="margin">Lib. 8. contra Celſum</note> both Men and Women, inſpired with a Spirit, have divinely foretold, what ſtrange and wondrous things they have drawn out of their ſecret Cells or Temples? how many things they have alſo foretold from the Entrals of their Sacrifices to thoſe that have conſulted them. How many things have been foreſhewed by other Prodigies; to ſome there have alſo been granted manifeſt apparitions of the Gods, the life of men is full of theſe matters, how many Cities have been built by the direction of theſe Oracles! how many have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped Peſtilence and Famines! how many Cities have Periſhed regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs or forgetful of their warnings! how many Colonies have been led out by their directions, and have been increaſed with great felicities while they have not neglected their commandments! how many both Princes and private Perſons have fared well or ill upon theſe accounts! how many being troubled for want of Children, by taking heed to them have obtained their deſires! how many have eſcaped the Anger of the Demons or devils! how many that have been Lame in their Members, have recovered their former ſoundneſs again! how many doing violence to their holy things, have forthwith been variouſly puniſhed! ſome have gone out of their Wits, ſome have of their own accord confeſſed their evil facts, others have made away themſelves others have fallen into in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable diſeaſes, nor wants there examples of ſome who have been kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a dreadful voice that hath proceeded forth from the cells or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places of their Temples.</q> Such ſtrange &amp; wonderful things could that Heathen boaſt of; concerning his falſe Gods and their wicked Worſhip, as I might alſo mention ſome inſtances that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes of in his tenth Book, <hi>de civitate Dei Cap</hi> 16. as of <hi>Aeneas</hi> his Images going of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from one place to another, of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arquinius</hi> cutting a Whetſtone through with a Raiſour, of a Woman with her girdle only faſtned thereto, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Ship that ſtuck ſo faſt in the River <hi>Tyb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> as it could not be moved, as a Teſtimony of her Chaſtity, and of another carrying Water in a ſieve from the ſaid River upon the like account: not to mention the ſtrange things done by <hi>Apollonius;</hi> which <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> would make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48544:25"/>
might be equallized with the Miracles wrought by Chriſt. Surely theſe, nor any, nor all of theſe, were no good evidences that they were Gods Church, and that they, or their doctrine or worſhip were approved of him, though the Signs and Wonders ſeem not much Inferior to what either <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his 8. Book before mentioned, relates of miraculous Cures done, or helps obtained at the Monuments of the Martyrs, or what ſome others have elſewhere related, as St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> or perhaps ſome of thoſe things mentioned by St. <hi>Auguſtine, lib.</hi> 21. <hi>de Civitate Dei, cap.</hi> 8.9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides this there is another thing to be ſaid to the Plea of the Roman Churches Miracles, that a great many of them are fained forg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed matters, and therein ſhe is a lying falſe Harlot, to go about to gull Souls with her lying and falſe deluſions, not but that thoſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> or others of the Fathers, might many of them be true, and God might work many miracles at ſuch places as were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the memory of the Martyrs, and of his holy ſervants, to draw people thereby to the beliefe and obedience of his truth, which they had confeſſed and ſuffered Martyrdom for, but doubtleſs Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and his inſtruments have alſo taken occaſion thence, either to work by Gods permiſſion diverſe ſtrange things, to puniſh thoſe that therefore departed from the purity of the worſhip of God and Chriſt, or alſo to counterfeit and pretend what was not indeed wrought to draw the minds of People into deceit; I ſhall not ſearch books for confirmation hereof, ſeeing if any man will vouchſafe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to peruſe what the Learned D. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> hath largly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed on this ſubject of their pretended miracles, he may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyed ſufficiently hereof, only I ſhall ſet down hear what the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Fryer, Mr. <hi>Anthony Aegan,</hi> in his recantation Sermon relates, which is to this purpoſe, That about ſeven years before his ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation Sermon made at <hi>London, April</hi> 6. 1673. a Prieſt near the City of <hi>Limrick,</hi> by name <hi>William Sarchwel,</hi> had for fifty ſhillings hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Woman to pretend her ſelf a Cripple from her birth, and that ſhe had a revelation that if ſhe dipt her ſelf in ſuch a Well while a Prieſt ſaid Maſs by the place, ſhe ſhould be recovered of her Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whereupon ſhe came halting at a time appointed to the Well, and returned out of it as one perfectly cured, which became a miracle to the people, and both got to the contriver a vaſt ſome of Mony, and confirmed the People in their ſuperſtition, which he tells us, the ſaid counterfeit Woman after ſome time upon ſome remorſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, confeſſed to him the ſaid <hi>Anthony Aegan,</hi> which he made her declare to the whole Congregation before he abſolved her, as alſo he tells of a Fryer of great note and zeal, that told him that he was at a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Convent beyond the Seas, where was the Image of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48544:26"/>
B. Virgin, made with a ſcrue in the head thereof, where they put in ſome water; and having a ſtring that came undeſerned to a place where the Fryers ſtood, when they thought the People had brought a good offering, then by the help of that ſtring they could unlooſe the ſcrue, and then the Image of the B. Virgin would ſeem to weep, and that was one of their Miracles which the relator ſaid was a great ſcandal to him, and that therefore he complained of it to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of their Order, who anſwered him, that ſhould he make a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in that particuler, that Convent ſhould ſtarve, to which he adds that the Monks of a certain Convent put a like cheat upon St. <hi>Barnard</hi> by an inſtrument, carrying the Voice to the Image of the ſaid Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> cauſing her to ſalute him with a <hi>ſalve Barnarde</hi> when he came into the Church, but he apprehending the Cheat, gave no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther return to the complement but this, that it is aſhame for a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to ſpeak in the Church, but adds the ſaid Fryer <hi>Aegan</hi> of all the fine ſtories, commend me to this new Miracle they talk of for the confirmation of tranſubſtantiation, <hi>viz.</hi> that in a certain place in the King of <hi>Spains</hi> dominion, as the Maſs was celebrated, all the perfect effigies &amp; proportion of a man roſe out of the hoſt, but when the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple came too near that they might ſee the Miracle plainly, he Vaniſhed away, on which he only relates a remark made by a Facetious Perſon to the relatot of it, you ſuppoſe, ſaid he, that it was Chriſt himſelf that appeared, and it ſeems upon the approach of the People he va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed away, which is the only circumſtance to make the Story cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, for he might ſuppoſe the People were come to eat him, and ſo he vaniſhed, I ſhall add to it this remark of my own, that many of their Miracles are ſuch as will not abide the ſearch and tryal, but upon a near approach to that end, vaniſh into nothing but pretence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion. Now if we put both theſe together, both that falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Perſons of falſe Religion may do ſigns and wonders, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially lying ſigns, and that many that are boaſted of in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are the lying cheats and deluſions of their Prieſts, then will their Plea of Miracles be too far from evidencing them to be the true Church of Chriſt, that it rather argues them guilty of being a lying Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is a brief character of the true Church and her Children in the book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> by which we may better judg of the truth and rightneſs of any Church, than by any or all thoſe fair Pleas that <hi>Rome</hi> makes for her ſelf, namely, that the true Church and its Children, are that ſociety and company of men that keep the commandments of God, and the faith or Teſtemony of Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.17. and 14.12. But, now if we bring the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to this teſt, I am ſure ſhe will be caſt, only let us mind that by keeping the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48544:26"/>
Commandments of God, is meant both the careful obſervation of them, to walk after them, and alſo the holding them forth ſincerely and purely without corrupting them, that others may know and walk after them alſo, and by keeping the faith and teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, is meant, the keeping it without ſpot or mixture of corruption with it, either by adding to, or taking from it. And ſurely if we take a little view of their carriage in either of them, we ſhall find them not a little faulty in both.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt as to the keeping of Gods commandments, which of them do they keep in the ſences above mentioned, not the firſt, for they have other Gods in the Scripture Language, beſide the only true God, the maker of all things, in Scripture Language they are called other Gods, to whom men give that adoration that belongs to God, and unto whom they perform religious worſhip or ſervice, asking of and expecting from them what is proper to God to give; ſo the Calves made by <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to be ſacrificed to, though intended as mediums to worſhip the true God by, yet they are called Gods that he made to himſelf, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 14.9. and ſo the golden Calf in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, though it was to <hi>Jehovah</hi> they pretended to Sacrifice &amp; keep a feaſt by it, yet they were charged with changing their glory (that is their God) therein into the ſimilitude of an Ox that eateth graſs and ſo intimately of making a new God to themſelves <hi>Exod.</hi> 32,4.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.19.20. now how many there are in the Roman Church, that according to thoſe Notions they make Gods to themſelves, it is not eaſy to determin. The hoſt in the Sacrament they ſtick not to own as God, God-man, &amp; to give divine adoration unto, inſomuch as one of their own Doctors acknowledges that the errors of thoſe that worſhip ſome Golden or Silver Statues, or ſome Images of any other materialls, for their God, as the Heathen worſhiped their Gods, or a Red Cloth hung upon the Top of Spear, as is reported of the <hi>Laplanders,</hi> or ſome live Animal, as of old the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did,<note place="margin">Fran. Coſter. Enchir. contro. verſ. Cap, 12.</note> were more tollerable than of thoſe who worſhiped a piece of Bread, as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the Chriſtians have done all over the World, for ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, if the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation be not true. And that, that Doctrine is not true, we have as good evidence as Chriſt gave to his Diſciples, that he was not a Spirit, that is, we may handle and ſee it, yea, and taſt and ſmell it too, as was ſaid above, yea, we have the ſame that we have, that the Cup is not tranſubſtantiated into the New Teſtament, and we have no more authority from the Scripture that the Bread is Tranſubſtantiated, than that the Cup is ſo Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated, nay, rather we have more ground to believe, that the Cup is changed into a divine writing, than that the Bread is chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Body, the very real and ſubſtantial Body of Chriſt. For
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48544:27"/>
it is expreſly ſaid, this Cup is the New Teſtament, but it is not ſaid, this Bread is my Body, nor this that was Bread is become my Body, and for ought that appears to the contrary in the Text, his Body being viſibly preſent, he might point to, or ſpeak of it, in ſaying, this is my Body, as he ſpeak of the Temple of his body, when walk-in the Temple, he ſaid to the Jews, <hi>Deſtroy ye this Temple, and in three days I will raiſe it up again;</hi> as our ſences tell us, the Cup is not the New Teſtament, but a Silver or Golden Cup or Challice, ſo the very ſame ſences tell us as plainly, that the Bread ſtill remains in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Bread, <hi>non ſubſtantiâ aut naturâ mutatus,</hi> not changed in ſubſtance or nature into God, or into the perſon of God-man the Lord Jeſus, beſides, it is their own Doctrine, that the change of the Elements depend upon the Intention of the Prieſt, ſo that if the Prieſt intend not, in ſaying the words, to make the body of Chriſt, it is not the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, but Bread ſtill, and then they are Idolaters that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it as God, and who can be certain of the Prieſts Intentions? not to mention again the many Saints, both Hees and Shees that they give ſuch adorations to as belongs only to God, and ask ſuch things of, as God only can give, ſo that they are notorious tranſgreſſors of the firſt commandment of God, and keep it not, and as to the ſecond they are ſo far from keeping it, and act ſo groſly contrary to it, that they expung it out of their Catechiſms; The third alſo they groſly violate in their Doctrine and practice about ſacred oaths, diſpence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them, and looſing men from the obligation of them, enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them by mental reſervations, and breaking ſolemn Oaths and promiſes, as in their breaking their promiſes with <hi>John Hus,</hi> and in the Popes diſpenſing with the Oath given by <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to <hi>Amurath</hi> the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperour or grand Sultan, and cauſing him to break his Truce with him, to the great ſcandal of Chriſtian Religion and ſlaughter of the Chriſtians. The <hi>Turk</hi> himſelf appealing to Chriſt, if he were indeed God, to revenge the perfidious Perjury of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> towards him, which he alſo did in the enſuing ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and deſtruction of them, but ſuch abuſe of Gods name, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving and diſpenſing with religious and ſolemn Oaths, yea, and with mens raſh ſwearing, they give allowance of in their Doctrines and treatiſes, as well as in their practices, yea, it was a thing that the above cited Fryer <hi>Aegan</hi> tells us, gave him one of his firſt diſguſts at their Religion, that when at his firſt being made a Fryer, he took one and twenty Oaths, and among them, that he would never come on Horſeback, that he would never ware ſhoes, that he would obey his ſuperiours in what ever he commanded, never examining the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of his commands; not to be aſhamed to beg, never to be out of his Fryers habit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet after all theſe oaths taken, his ſuperiour
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48544:27"/>
told him, that he muſt take his former garments and return in the ſame Poſture that he came in (which was on Horſeback, with Sword and Piſtols, and gay Apparrel) and go ſee his friends, though quite contrary to his oaths, from which he would abſolve him. If here was not a taking Gods name in vain, and a notorious leading men to debauch their conſciences, I know not what is: as for the fourth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, they keep not that, while they keep Markets on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, and leſs obſerve it than many of their own inſtituted holy days: the fifth commandment, how little they reguard their often ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving Children from ingagements, to honour their Parents and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them, yea, their ſtirring up Children ſomtimes againſt them, (as <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth ſtirred up <hi>Henry,</hi> the Son, againſt his Father <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> the ſecond, Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi>) and how often they have diſcharged ſubjects from their due allegiance and obedience to their lawful Sovereigns, &amp; ſtirred them up to rebel and riſe in War againſt them; both our own Cronicles and the Hiſtories of other Nations do abundantly evidence. And then as for the ſixth commandment, their Murthering of Princes, and the many great Slaughters and Maſſacres, yea, deſtructions both of Souls and Bodies, occaſioned and cauſed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church and her Biſhops, before hinted at, ſufficiently declare how little care they have thereof. That they little reguard the ſeventh, both their forbiding Marriage to their Prieſts, without any order or command of God and Chriſt to that purpoſe, nay, contrary to the expreſs permiſſion and allowance thereof of God in the Scriptures (for both our Lord Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf choſe Married Perſons to be Apoſtles, at leaſt <hi>Peter</hi> was ſuch when he choſe him, for we read before, that of his Wives Mother, <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.30. with 3.16. Which he would not have done ſurely, had he judged a Wedded State incompatible or inconſiſtent with the Miniſtry which he inſtituted, yea, and that St. <hi>Peter</hi> and other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, led their Wives about with them, when they were Apoſtles, is evident in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. And the Apoſtle expreſly, both in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders about Biſhops, and in thoſe about Deacons orders, and much more allows, that they be Husbands of one Wife, and have their Children in ſubjection, which they would not have done, had they forbidden Marriage to the Biſhops and Miniſters of the Church, or judged it unfit for them, as theſe, according to his predictions of falſe Teachers, that would depart from the faith, do, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.4.11.12. with 4.12.3.) By which means they often put them upon the practice of uncleanneſs, whoredoms, furnications, and the like miſchiefs; and allow them to keep Concubines for Money; beſides, the Practice of Sodomy, even in the Popes themſelves, ſome of them, and the notorious Wickedneſs of one of their Cardinals, that wrote and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48544:28"/>
Wrote &amp; publiſhed a Book in commendation thereof, &amp; their allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publick Stews for Mony, even in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf are ſufficient Proofs. And that they as little keep the eighth Commandment, their inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble covetouſneſs, and many frauds to get Mony, ſome whereof have by the way been hinted at, yea, their graſping whole Kingdoms to themſelves, from their lawful Princes, as they did a great part of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi> yea, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf from the Emperours to which they belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in King <hi>Johns</hi> time, and taking away by force the Kingdoms of ſome Princes from them, and giving them to others whom they have incouraged to get them from them, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> and the attempts of their Popes, and Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt our late Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent demonſtrations, beſides, the moſt horrible theft of all others they are guilty of in ſtealing or taking forcibly from men the word of God, not ſuffering men to know or be inſtructed into that; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in taking away the key of knowledg, and ſhutting up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt them, and robbing their Souls thereof; a theft which God complained of in the falſe Prophets of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Behold I am againſt the Prophets which ſteal my word every one from his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> Jer. 23.30. Againſt the ninth Commandment is all their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching and branding falſly, as <hi>Hereticks,</hi> thoſe that will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to their corruptions, ſtirring up Princes and People againſt them, to make Havock of them. And that the tenth commandment is little ſet by, their Doctrine that denyes the firſt ſtirrings and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Sin to be Sins, and their Doctrine of venial Sins, and their inſatiable covetouſneſs, may be evidence enough, ſo that they are hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly guilty of not keeping the commandments of God, the like may be obſerved too, of their keeping the things given in commandment by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that they keep none of his commandments purely and incorruptly, for whereas he commanded Baptiſm into the Name of the Father, &amp; of the Son, &amp; of the Holy Ghoſt, they have corrupt that with many deviſes, as of oyl, and cream, and ſpettle, and the like Fopperies; his commandment of his Supper, to take and break and eat Bread, ſet a part with bleſſing to that purpoſe, and drinking the Cup in Remembrance of him, and as a commemoration of his death, they have horribly corrupted and changed into a ſacrifice propitiatory and unbloody, available for obtaining remiſſion of Sins, for the quick and for Dead, and into private Maſſes, and half Communions, and the Pageantry of carrying the conſecrated Hoſt as a God in Proceſſion, the command of Preaching the word ſincerely they have exchanged into teaching for <hi>Doctrines</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> that is, their own precepts and deviſes, and his command about prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications unto God, they have corrupted by injoyning Prayers in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48544:28"/>
unknown Tongue, and to others beſides God, even to Saints and Angels.</p>
            <p>But what needed I to have been ſo larg in going over theſe ſeveral commandments, when the complexion of much of their divinity is a clear patronage of all manner of Sin and Naughtineſs, while they promiſe to men the pardon thereof, upon ſo eaſy termes, as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being at ſome ſmall time before they dye, grieved that they have ſinned, though, without any real contrition of heart for it, or love to God, and ſo hearty ſorrow that they have offended him, as ſpringing therefrom, provided that they receive but the Sacrament, as they will have it, of their extream Unction, and the abſolution of one of their Prieſts, and have deviſed a Purgatory, in which, after death, they may be Purifyed, though they continue till death in their Sins, from the pains of which alſo, they perſwade men they may be ſoon delivered by the propitiatory ſacrifices, which they ſay they can, and do day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make in their Maſſes, both for the quick and for the dead, and by the indulgences which are in the Popes diſpoſe, and which for ſuch ſums of Mony given to their Church-men, or for ſuch uſes as they preſcribe, as for the procuring Maſſes, Dirgies, and ſuch like fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries they propoſe to ſale? what are all theſe deviſes of this cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Church and its Church-men, but ways of making merchandiſe of mens Souls? and an incouraging them in and unto an impenitent breach of all Gods commandments all their days? for who that loves his luſts, and lives in any pleaſurable or profitable way of Sin, will much reguard the ceaſing therefrom, or any commands of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it, ſo long as his guides and leaders, that pretend to have the keys of Heaven in their hands, aſſure them that if but an hour or two before their deaths, they confeſs their Sins, and are ſorry that they have endangered their Souls thereby, and be a little attrite or troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for them, receiving abſolution from the Prieſt, and their extreme Unction, they may by the vertue of the Sacraments, to convey grace, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> be ſecured againſt damnation? and be eaſed too in, and freed from their Purgatory pains, if they be but bountiful to their Church, and its Prieſts, by the benefit of their devotions, and the Saints Supererrogations? ſo that by this firſt part of the Touch-ſtone, they appear clearly convicted of being far from being an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Church, yea, or a true and right Church of Chriſt, eſpecially, if we alſo take in what ſome of them aſſert, and their doctrine of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, therefore, makes ſafe for all to believe, <hi>viz.</hi> that no man is bound of neceſſity to love God, but that is a work or frame of more perfection, without which, obſerving their Church Orders, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving their Sacraments, they may be ſaved. Surely by our Saviours doctrine, to love God is the firſt and great Commandment, and that they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48544:29"/>
that teach that men may be ſaved though deſtitute thereof, cannot be under the commendation of keeping Gods commandments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And as much faulty are they, with reference to the other branch of the character of the true Church, oppoſed to the falſe Church, or the Beaſt and his Image worſhippers, namely, the keeping the faith or teſtimony of Jeſus, which they keep not that corrupt it, and add their mixtures to and with it, as the falſe Apoſtles kept not the faith of Jeſus, though they might hold as truths all the Articles of the Creed, and teach them to others, while they added thereto the neceſſity of being Circumciſed, and of keeping the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> unto Salvation, no more than they would be commended for keeping for any ones uſe good and wholſome Wine commited to their cuſtody and charge, who would indeed deminiſh nothing of it, but yet would mix with it ſome of thoſe <hi>Stygian</hi> Waters, which had a poyſonous nature in them, or other poyſons whereby they might be made deadly to them that drink thereof; ſuch a Perſon might indeed plead that he had kept by him all the Wine depoſited with him, and took nothing of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, yea, and that he gave out again all that other keepers of it, who keep it Pure, and give it out ſuch as it is given, do, and ſomething more, but I ſuppoſe with no likement or commendation of him that commits it to him for the benefit of thoſe that will drink of it; juſt ſuch keepers, that is to ſay, corrupters of the faith of Jeſus, are the Papiſts and their Church. They retain with them indeed the whole Bible, and all the Goſpel, and Goſpel truths therein, but ſo as to keep them in their Bibles from the generallity of the People, that they may not read or hear them read to them, yea, and they retain with them, and poſſibly Preach to the People, and Teach them all the Articles of the Creed, at leaſt in an unknown Latin Tongue, or if they alſo interpret them, yet to be ſure, they teach them many other things, as matters of faith neceſſary to be believed by them, as much as any of the ſaid Articles, though they be quite different from all that Chriſt and his Apoſtles delivered to the Church to be believed by us, as for inſtance, they teach that God the Father, and Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt, are one God in three Perſons, to be believed on, and called upon by Men, but they corrupt that with this addition of their own, that the Saints alſo are to be called on, and that they ought to believe on them, to receive help by their interceſſions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſhiped by them; they teach that Chriſt is the Son of God and the Saviour of the World, that he dyed for our Sins, and offered up a Propitiatory Sacrifice to God for the whole World, but then they add and mix of their own therewith, that their Prieſts can &amp; do day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make him of a Wafer, and offer him up as an effectual unbloody ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the quick and dead to, and that they ought to believe and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48544:29"/>
expect to receive the forgiveneſs of their Sins through their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing him, a moſt horrible impiety and indignity to his Croſs and Paſſion, and the alone virtue and efficacy thereof, and a monſtrous addition to, and corruption of the faith, once delivered of God to the Saints in his Apoſtles doctrine. They hold and teach that Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and aſcended into Heaven, and ſits at the Right Hand of God, but they mix therewith, and teach their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Followers to believe, that the ſame very real Body that ſuffered and is in Heaven, is alſo dayly in the Hoſt at their Maſs, and is hung up in the Pix or Box that they put him into, and that they carry up and down when they pleaſe in Proceſſion, and that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tear him with their Teeth and eat him,<note place="margin">Lib. de Natura Deorum.</note> and therein they do what the Heathen <hi>Cicero</hi> abhorred to think of in their <hi>Pagan</hi> worſhip, for he ſaid, <hi>quem tam amentem eſſe putas, qui illud, quo veſcatur, Deum credat eſse?</hi> that is, who thinkeſt thou is ſo mad, as to think that to be a God that he eats or is fed with? thoſe Papiſts are ſo mad as to think and teach ſo, they hold and teach that there is a Heaven to reward the righteous, and a Hell to Puniſh the wicked, and ſo our Saviour deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in his faith or teſtimony, but withal they add, that there is a third place between both, called Purgatory, wherein Souls that are not fit for Heaven when they dye, may be purged, by enduring pains and torments there, and that the Pope hath the keys of this place to, and can let Souls out of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this Chriſt never taught nor his Apoſtles, they believe and teach that there is a Holy Ghoſt, and that he is to be believed in, but they teach alſo corruptly, that he is confined, as it were, to them of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that their determinations, or the determinations of their Popes out of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, are his infallible Oracles, to be as much believed, and held as faſt as (or more than) the ſayings of the holy Prophets &amp; Apoſtles in the Scriptures. They teach that there is a holy Catholick Church, but they add and mix with that alſo this Poyſonful Doctrine, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> only are that Church, and that men are to reſolve their faith into its ſayings and concluſions, and that the Pope is the viſible Head of the whole Catholick Church, and Chriſts Vicar on earth; they teach a Communion of Saints, but they teach alſo with it a worſhip of thoſe that are deceaſed and canonized by the Pope, and that they may and ought to be invocated; they teach remiſſion of Sins, but they corrupt the doctrine of it by teaching that it is to be ſought for, not only in believing on, and yielding obedience to Chriſt, but alſo by their prayers to, and invocation of the Saints, by Pilgrimages and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of their own, or others impoſing on them, by the merits of the Saints, and not by Chriſts only; by the virtue of their Maſs, and the very reception of their Sacraments, and the like; they hold and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48544:30"/>
teach the Reſurrection of the Body, and Life everlaſting; but they teach alſo this corrupt doctrine, that life everlaſting may be merited of God by our good works, for ſo ſome of them do teach, that good works do truly merit grace in this world, and glory in the next; and that good works of juſt perſons are of themſelves worthy of the reward of Eternal life without any Covenant or acceptation of God; yea, and that no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of dignity comes to juſt mens works by the Merits or Perſon of Chriſt, which the ſame works ſhould not otherwiſe have had, had they been done by the ſame grace, beſtowed by the liberality of God alone without Chriſt, and therefore alſo they ſay, that after grace infuſed, our works are ſo perfectly Meritorious of life that it cannot be denied them, and that therefore they never requeſt of God, by the Merits of Chriſt, that the reward of eternal Life may be given to their worthy and meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious works; but that by Chriſt, grace may be given them, to inable them to merit worthily that reward; and much to the ſame purpoſe may be found in ſome of their Writers, as <hi>Vaſquez</hi> his Diſputations evidence. So that inſtead of keeping the Faith, and Teſtimony of Jeſus, they egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly corrupt, and mix it with their own additions, which yet they require as much to be believed and practiſed upon, as they do any Articles of the Faith delivered in the holy Scriptures, and as much as the belief of the neceſſity of Circumciſion, and of keeping the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and practiſed upon by the falſe Apoſtles. So that to any that will mind the Scriptures, and impartially will weigh what is ſaid in them, and compare therewith the way of this Church, they cannot, unleſs they be ſtark-blind, or wilfully cloſe their eyes, but ſee and conclude that this Roman Church is far from being a true or right Church of Chriſt, much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs can it be the only and Catholick Church, or Infallible in her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Dictates; which things being ſo, it might be marvailed that all men do not fly out of, and from her Communion that have any care of their Souls, and deſire the everlaſting Salvation of them, and that may be the matter of another inquiry and conſideration.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whence it is that ſo many ſtill continue in her Communion after ſo many convictions of the evil of her ways, by ſo many learned and able Proteſtants, and Reformed Writers and Preachers, in ſo many learned Treatiſes? yea, and not only ſo, but that many fall to her alſo that had rejected her, or have lived under the knowledge of the Scriptures, and the enjoyments of that light from them, by which they might be able to diſcern, and be led to beware of her?</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, in both its branches, it may be noted firſt of all, that this is nothing more than what the Holy Ghoſt fore-ſaw, and fore-ſignified in the Holy Scriptures; for in the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> it is evident that Myſtery <hi>Babilon</hi> would have many commit Fornication with her until her deſtruction comes upon her, yea, and they alſo many
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48544:30"/>
of them no mean perſons; for it is ſaid, that the Kings of the Earth who have committed Fornication, and lived deliciouſly with her, ſhall bewail her, and lament for her when they ſee the ſmoak of her burning, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a far off for fear of her torment, and ſaying, alas, alas, that great City Babilon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Merchants of the Earth ſhall weep and mourn over her, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and every Shipmaſter, and all the company in Ships, and Sailers, and as many as trade by Sea, ſtood a far off and cryed when they ſaw the Smoak of her burning, <hi>&amp;c. Revelations</hi> 18, 9, 10, 11, 17, 18. Yea, and the holy Ghoſt ſignifies, that after the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the everlaſting Goſpel, by an Angel flying in the midſt of Heaven, to them that dwell on the Earth, warning them to fear God, and give glory to him, and worſhip him that made Heaven and Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction from and in oppoſition to all other falſe objects of worſhip, ſuch as are in <hi>Babylon,</hi> as the Beaſt and his Image, and after another Angel following and ſaying, <hi>Babilon</hi> is fallen, is fallen, that great City, both fallen from her firſt love, fallen into falſe and corrupt worſhip, and fallen too from her firſt dignity and ſplendor which ſhe had as <hi>Babylon,</hi> as that falſe Harlot that made all Nations drink of the Wine of the wrath of her Fornications, yet it is ſuppoſed that ſome might and would yet worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14, 6, 7, 8, 9. which may denote the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Babiloniſh Idolatry after the Goſpel Preached by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, calling men to the right and true worſhip, and after the decay and fall of the Roman Church from her priſtine ſplendor and grandeur; for the falling of her may be one thing, and her Plagues and burning may be another thing, between which, yet ſhe may be ſtrugling to recover herſelf, and while ſo, ſhe may have ſome, not only continuing in her communion to the laſt, but ſome alſo joyning themſelves to her Idol worſhip that were ſometimes not joyning with her therein; to which purpoſe alſo may be interpreted theſe two expreſſions concerning the man of Sin the myſtical <hi>Jereboam</hi> that cauſed <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Sin, that the Lord ſhall conſume him with the breath of his mouth, that is, by his word and ſpirit in the Preaching of the Goſpel as the Papacy hath been, and is at this day under a conſumption thereby, and then at length he ſhall deſtroy him by the brightneſs of his coming, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. Now as it is in conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, we know perſons that labour thereof, will ſometimes be very ill and languiſh, and ſometimes chear again, and revive, and ſeem to be on the mending hand, get up a little, and be ſomewhat brisk, ſo may it be with the man of Sin; he may ſeem ſometime in his conſumptive ſtate to be getting heart again, and men may think he will recover his former health, and get rid of that deadly wound, that by the Sword of the Goſpel he hath received, and beſtir himſelf then again more vigorouſly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48544:31"/>
than before, that he may keep up, and no more fall down; but yet at the brightneſs of the Lords appearance, he will thereby totally ruin and deſtroy him, but to ſpeak a little diſtinctly to the cauſes and reaſons both.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the continuance of ſo many ſtill to cleave to her after ſhe hath been ſo detected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the falling of any to her after ſo great and long a diſcovery of her, and declining from her.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the firſt of theſe, with reſpect to her ſelf, and thoſe that are more properly the conſtitutive and eſſential parts of her, the Church as diſtinguiſhed by her ſelf from the Laity, or people adhering to her, and eſpecially the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe being as ſhe is called, and as we have ſhewed, a Whore, a Harlot, it fares with her as it doth with other Whores, that is, as ſuch a one that is a Whore, getting gain and profit to her ſelf by her Whoredom, and finding pleaſure and ſweetneſs therein, is hardned againſt the diſcoveries of her falſe practiſes, and uſually goeth on impenitently in her Trade, becauſe of the profit and gain accruing to her thereby, and eſpecially if She be Courted by great and rich Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Princes, they give her conſiderable gifts of Riches, Honours, and Dignities, and makes but a Tuſh at the Laws, Threatning Puniſhment, or Death, for ſuch practiſes, ſhe finding no effect or Execution of them for a long time to appear againſt her, by occaſion whereof, She flatters her Self that it will be never otherwiſe with her than it is, but that She ſhall always eſcape puniſhment. So fares it with this Adulterous Church, ſhe hath found, and finds ſo much gain and profit, of worldly Intereſt, Riches, Honour, Dignity, accruing to her ſince her trucking with Kings, and Princes, and Emperors, and obtaining of them to be owned and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in all her pretenſions as the Catholick Church, the Church that all perſons ought to comply with, and ſubmit to, and that her Head and Biſhop ſhould be taken to be the Vicar of Chriſt, the higheſt power on earth, that its no marvail if She repent not of her ſo ſweet and gainful a Trade, but by all means endeavours to keep up her credit that ſhe may be ſtill ſo courted and careſſed; and if ſhe hath gotten a wound that hath threatned her life, that ſhe endeavours to get cured, and to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her Priſtine ſtrength, which if ſhe do recover, we expect ſhe will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her old trade of Strumpetry and Blood-ſhedding, as hard or harder than ever, that ſo ſhe may ſecure her ſelf, if poſſible, from the threatned puniſhment and judgment, ordered of God and denounced in his Name againſt her by us, which maugre all her power and pollicy, ſhe ſhall not be able to eſcape, for ſtrong is the Lord God that judgeth her; the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of whoſe appearing that Man of Sin ſhall not be able to endure. To this purpoſe, that ſhe may recover her Priſtine ſtrength and vigour, and follow her accurſed Trade with the greater fervour or fury; her Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians, as ſo many Phyſitians, are at work very hard, beating their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48544:31"/>
brains, and uſing all their skill and Induſtry to make her whole again: and wo to us for a while if her diſeaſe be cured, and the Beaſts deadly wound be healed; for then will be indeed accompliſhed more fully that which is written in <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.15, 16, 17. but in the mean time there are many cleave to her, and have all along cleaved to her, Becauſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Many of them are kept from, or have not the opportunity of ſeeing and hearing what is evidenced againſt her, though perhaps they have heard ſome rumour of the Goſpel Preached to them that dwell on the Earth, and of the Fall of <hi>Babylon</hi> in part from her Priſtine power and ſplendour, many are kept in ignorance, both of the Scriptures, and of the Sermons and Diſcourſes in Writing of the Proteſtant parties, and many neglect to inquire into them, and ſo come not to know what is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videnced againſt her; her Pandors or Merchants ſetting themſelves to keep them in Ignorance and Error, to keep up their own grandeur and worldly Intereſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The cunning Sophiſtry and deceits of her Prieſts and Jeſuits, men of a ſeared Conſcience and ſtiff Impudence, who like <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres,</hi> who withſtood <hi>Moſes</hi> from or in his diſcovering the truth of God to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the Egyptians, do ſtand againſt the truth, and the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of it, and the diſcoverers of the Romiſh Frauds and Impoſtures, prevail much with many who are apt to reſolve their faith into their learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſubtlety, authority, and appearing Piety and wiſdom, (even as the ſlights of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> prevailed with <hi>Pharoah</hi> and many of the Egyptians) ſo as that though they hear and may hear, or read the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the learned Proteſtants, wherein they have detected their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, yet they do not ſeriouſly Ponder or weigh them, or are blinded from diſcerning the truth by the miſts they caſt before them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Worldly intereſt holds in many both of the Kings and Greater Perſons, their intereſt being interwoven with thoſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> and where the Kings and Princes of the earth commit fornication with her, they do by their Laws in many places, made againſt them that reject her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and their rigour and cruelty, deter many from liſtening to, and conſidering what is ſaid againſt her; yea, and they keep out ſuch diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers or diſcoveries of her lewdneſs; that otherwiſe would be afforded to them, as was predicted in <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.15, 16, 17. and where their Laws are not ſo cruel, yet by their bad examples, and their indulging their favours to her followers, they keep in many from liſtening to what would tend to withdraw them from her; the moſt of men not ſearching ſo much with ſincere endeavors after what is true and right, as minding and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in what is uppermoſt in the world, and worſhipping in truth its Power and Grandeur (which I take to be that which the Holy Ghoſt in the Apocalyps, calls the Beaſt) more than any other God beſides.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The dependance that the younger perſons have upon the Elder, or
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48544:32"/>
others related to them, the Children upon their Parents, and Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folks, and Friends one upon another, and the reſpect they have one for another, is ſome cauſe alſo of many being detained therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carryed away with ſuch as they have, ſuch dependance upon, or reſpect unto, eſpecially the being Educated under ſuch Principles as have been maintained by, and tranſmitted to them from their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Progenitors, for many generations proves a powerful motive to retain, and not reject thoſe principles what ever may be offered to detect and diſcover the evil of them, few being ſo redeemed from the vain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations received by tradition from their Fathers and Forefathers, or from the Earth and Men; even from earthly affections, and from their reſpects to, and dependances on men by the Blood of Chriſt, minded and regarded by them, as it hath been ſhed for them, as to renounce all ſuch reſpect to Fathers and Forefathers, earthly affections, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on, and reſpects to men, and to follow after Chriſt ſingly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely where-ever he by his Word and Doctrine would lead them, or ſo as to make ſuch due and diligent inquiry and ſearch into the truth, as it is in him, that they might underſtand it, and be led and guided by it. And then</p>
            <p n="5">5. The juſt and righteous Judgment of God, it is to harden both this Harlot and her Adherents, for their unfaithfulneſs in ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or not admitting the truth of God; but either ſlightly neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inquiry after it, or againſt evident ſhinings of it cloſing their eyes, leſt they ſhould ſee with their eyes, or hear with their ears, or underſtand with their hearts what they ſee would tend to convert them from their gainful and delicious intereſts and enjoyments. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as Gods Judgments were upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them; for as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> hardning themſelves, and doing wickedly againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> were left of God to their hardneſs or hardened by him, that he might glorify himſelf on them in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: ſo it is with this falſly Infallible, but truly inflexible im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Church, he gives her and her Adherents up to their own hearts luſts, and to walk in their Idolatrous and bloody ways to fill up the meaſure of their iniquities, that he might glorify himſelf in executing upon them the Doom and Judgment that is written con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Though alſo ſome occaſion of hardning this Church, and ſome advantage her ſubtle Factors take to harden people in their obſtinate cleaving to her from the too great diviſions found, and by them alſo fomented among us Proteſtants, with the too much iniquity alſo practiſed among us, and ſome harſh Principles about Gods Decrees of Reprobation in ſome among us. Whence they poſſeſs the minds of her Followers that they are in a better ſtate, more at unity, and perhaps many of them leſs outwardly vitious (though not their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality)
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48544:32"/>
and more devout than they ſhould be, ſhould they forſake their Communion to embrace ours. Yea, and they can aggravate our diviſions, &amp; repreſent them, as if they were the juſt judgment of God upon us for deſerting her Communion; though that be as falſe as, and no truer than that the Diviſions, Feuds, and Wars among us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, both Papiſts and Proteſtants, are the juſt judgment of God upon us for caſting off Heatheniſm, or for not turning <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Mahumetans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. To which add the fair paints and cunning carriage of this Harlot; for as it is with other Whores, they may and often have as handſom bodies, as comely faces, as ſmooth carriages, as good parts, and witty winning behaviour as honeſt Women and chaſt Matrons. Yea, ſometimes they may in ſome of thoſe things, if not in all, exceed them, and being rich or richly maintained, may, and often have as coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparel, as rich ornaments and Jewels, as other honeſter perſons; nay, and where they find defect of beauty, can ſupply it by art, paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their faces with ſuch freſh &amp; lively colours, as ſhall make them ſeem young and youthful, when in truth and underneath they are black and deformed. Even ſo this <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church being a rich and ſubtle Harlot, is not void of many taking and winning matters, wherewith ſhe ſets forth her ſelf to draw or keep in Lovers, and <hi>trims her way to ſeek love,</hi> as the Prophet ſaid of the Adulterous Church that did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede her, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.33. Yea, to her may well be applyed that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Nahum</hi> to the bloody City: <hi>That ſhe is a well-favoured Harlot,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Miſtriſs of witchcrafts, that ſelleth Nations through her whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and Families through her Witchcrafts,</hi> Nah. 3.4. For it is true that ſhe hath in her Perſons indued with great natural parts and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Men of learning and policy; and that ſhe hath many good gifts from God by Jeſus Chriſt, wherewith ſhe might and ought to ſerve and pleaſe him. Yea, ſhe hath Jewels of his gold and of his ſilver as it were, which he in her better ſtate was pleaſed mercifully and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, freely to impart unto her. But as it is the fault of Harlots to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the gifts of God &amp; men to diſhoneſt arts and ends, ſo it fares with this Church alſo; for ſhe doth as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did before her, of whom the Lord ſaith; <hi>That ſhe took of her garments</hi> (namely that he had given her, for he found her naked and in her blood) <hi>and decked her high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with divers colours, and played the Harlot thereupon. And ſhe took her fair jewels of his gold and of his ſilver, and made to her ſelf Images of a male, and committed Whoredom with them; and ſhe took her broidred garments and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, and ſet his Oyl and his Incenſe before them, and his meat which he gave her, even fine flower, and oyl, and honey wherewith he fed her, ſhe ſet it even before them for a ſweet ſavour,</hi> &amp;c. Ezek. 16.16, 17, 18, 19. Even ſo we may ſay of this Church, that ſhe ſerves her Idols with the gifts of God, and makes uſe even of the truths that ſhe hath received from Chriſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48544:33"/>
and his ordinances to make up an Image of them, as mixed with her inventions (a frame of Religion) which ſhe worſhips, and cauſeth all to worſhip. Yea, and ſhe decks her ſelf with her natural parts, and gifts, Moral Virtues, and acquired Sciences, and with many things which ſhe hath received from God. But not that ſhe might ſingly ſerve Chriſt therewith, but to ſeek love from the Kings, and Princes, and people of the World, &amp; to commit fornication with them; and many are taken and led captive with theſe her ornaments, that is, with her Learning, ſeeming Devotion, Charity and Piety, which are all made uſe of ſubſerviently to the grand deſign of making her ſelf a Goddeſs, or an Object of worſhip by the poor ſimple Souls that ſhe that way deludes, and as artifices of drawing them to commit adultery with her. With ſuch things ſhe paints and guilds over her ſelf to inamour men of her, and make them her Vaſſals, that ſhe might inrich her ſelf, though with the ſpoil of their Souls. As in a viſion was forerepreſented by the Holy Ghoſt concerning her in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. while the holy man ſaw her as a <hi>Woman arrayed in purple and ſcarlet colour, and deckt or gilded with Gold, and pretious Stones; and Pearls, having a golden Cup in her hand, in which ſhe gives forth her abominations.</hi> Signifying hereby what a gawdy Church ſhe would be in her appearance and worſhip, and how ſhe would be adorned with many fine glittering and rich colours, the better to inamour the Kings and people of the Earth on her. Yea, and as crafty and witty Whores can conform themſelves to the different tempers of their Paramours, the better to work upon and captivate, and keep their affections: ſo it is with this wiley Church, and her Panders. For thoſe that are melancholly, or of a more grave ſober temper, or religiouſly inclined, ſhe can entertain them with Books of Devotion, formes of Penance, rules of Mortification, and many learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſcourſes that may ſuit their humors; but yet, ſo as they muſt take in therewith her Superſtitions; and ſhe hath her Monaſteries and Nunneries, places of ſeparation from the World, in a ſort to be devout in, if they be ſo diſpoſed: and for thoſe that have deſires for Heaven, ſhe can ſhew them (as ſhe pretends) a certain way whereby they may not only obtain, but merit it too, and to that purpoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites them to much devotion to God, and to the Saints, and provokes them to bounty, and works of charity, though ſhe poyſons them with her Doctrine of Merit, tending to puff them up, and corrupts all their good things with the ſowre and evil leaven of Idolatry, and other falſe Opinions before reproved. For as the Apoſtle ſaith of the falſe Apoſtles, that they could <hi>transform themſelves into the Miniſters of righteouſneſs, while corrupting men in and from the faith, they were for all their goodly appearance, in reality the Meſſengers of Sathan; and that they made a fair ſhew in the fleſh, and gloried in appearance, not in heart,</hi> 2 Corinth.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48544:33"/>
11.13, 15. and 5.12. Gall. 6.12. So is it with theſe men. They are (as Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> hath very well and worthily obſerved, and in his <hi>Sermon</hi> upon that Text manifeſted them to be) Wolves in ſheeps cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Religioniſts that walk after their directions, are corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſpoiled by them. For if <hi>the ſpeaking with the tongue of men and Angels, gift of Prophecy, and underſtanding all Myſteries, and all Knowledge;</hi> yea, and <hi>Faith, ſo as to remove Mountains, and the giving all a mans goods to feed the poor, and his body to be burnt, will not profit him if he have not love or charity,</hi> 1 Cor 13.1, 2, 3. what profit think we can accrue to this Church, or to any of its Devotioniſts from all their Devotions, Gifts, Liberality, Penances, or whatever elſe is done by them while they are guilty of groſs Idolatry, and corruptions of the Faith, as is before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videnced. Surely no Idolater hath true love to God, nor any that is partaker with the Blood-thirſty, the guilt whereof lies upon this Church, and all in its Communion. When the Apoſtle commends Charity, it is a <hi>Charity out of a pure heart, and a good conſcience, and Faith unfeigned,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.5. which cannot be where Idolatry and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and corruption of the Faith take place, however liberal they may be in Almſdeeds to the poor; which the Apoſtle alſo ſuppoſeth may be, where that love and charity which is ſo neceſſary and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is yet wanting. Suppoſe the <hi>Gallathians</hi> ſeduced by the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to believe the neceſſity of Circumciſion, and the obſervation of the Laws of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhould have been alſo perſwaded by them to have retired themſelves into Monaſteries, and ſpent their time in Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and been free to give all they had to feed the poor, would any or all thoſe things have profited them under that perſwaſion? I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not, ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If they were circumciſed, Chriſt would profit them nothing,</hi> Gall. 6.2. If Chriſt would profit them nothing, ſurely much leſs would thoſe things, or whatever elſe could have been done by them. And doubtleſs if the corrupting their Faith by Circumciſion would have ſo marred all their Religion, much more will Idolatry, Superſtition, and the other Iniquities before detected in the Roman Communion, marr all their fineſt, and otherwiſe moſt laudable actions. But then on the other ſide, this wiley Church, like a wiley Strumpet, hath other entertainments for perſons of other tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers or diſpoſitions; and if they have a mind to live looſly, and in the practice of any Wickedneſs, they have plaiſters to skin over ſuch Ulcers; they can fit them with looſe Doctrines and Principles, they can hold them in the Roman Communion, by telling them, that if they confeſs to the Prieſt once a year or oftner, and receive Abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from their ſins upon ſome petty Penances, and ſeeming Auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the fleſh (which yet they may upon pretty light Devotions, or for mony have Indulgencies in) they may receive pardon for all their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48544:34"/>
forepaſt faults, yea, perhaps for a great many years too, or for a great time to come, and if they continue in ſin till death, returning to what they have confeſſed; yet if but an hour or two before their death they can but ſend for a Prieſt, and make confeſſion of their ſins with ſome attrition or grief that their condition is no better, though they be not contrite or broken in heart for their ſins, nor have any love of God; yet having the Prieſts abſolution, and being anointed with their Extream Unction, they are ſecured from Hell and damnation. Indeed they may be unfit for Heaven, as the fooliſh Virgins were, that ſlumbred and ſlept till it was proclaimed that the Bridegroom came, and then not having Oyl in their Veſſels, their Lamps were gone out; ay, but they ſhall go but to Purgatory at the worſt, and be purged by thoſe pains for ſometime; and from thence alſo they may be ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed by vertue of the over-much Oyl in the wiſe Virgins Veſſels, that is, by vertue of the meritorious works of Supererrogation done by their more religious Votaries, and Canonized Saints, and by the Maſſes and Sacrifices offered for the quick and the dead, and other Devotions performed by their living Prieſts; eſpecially if they give a conſiderable ſum of mony to them to purchaſe their Devotions for them when they dy, and then they may in a ſhort time too be at reſt therefrom. And theſe are fine pleaſing baits to hook and hold in the Souls of vitious perſons. Now who that's religiouſly inclined, but by a conceit of meriting, will be obſervant of the rules of ſuch a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? And who that loves his ſins but will like ſuch a Doctrine and Religion, as gives them ſo good encouragement to hold them faſt, and propounds ſuch eaſy remedies to ſecure them from the dreadful puniſhments of them? And that's a main reaſon of ſo many great and ſmall being held faſt in the arms of this loving Church, that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her ſelf gay, and gawdy, and deckt, and painted with fine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, hath the wit, or craft, and ſubtlety to bait her Hooks accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the humors of the ſeveral perſons for whom ſhe fiſhes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodates her ſelf to the ſeveral diſpoſitions of her Paramours; to be either more ſolitary and ſullen, or more pleaſant and gameſome, as may ſuit beſt with their conſtitution. What we have ſaid upon this firſt Head, to the reaſons of ſo many being held ſtill in her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, may ſuffice to that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And truly in anſwer to the inquiry in its ſecond branch, ſome things of what is ſaid to the former might be repeated again, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther referred unto by us, as cauſes thereof; namely, of the falling off of ſo many to her that have been delivered from her, and brought up under that light by which they might ſo diſcover her falſe colours, as to keep from her. As the ſubtlety of her Emiſſaries and Factors, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now more liberty amongſt us to negotiate for her than formerly;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48544:34"/>
and the occaſions of offence miniſtred by our own diviſions, and the too many miſcarriages found among us, eſpecially in ſome tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the late times; which thoſe Emiſſaries want neither skill nor will to improve to the furtherance of their deſigns: and alſo the fair flouriſhes that ſhe by them makes, eſpecially in theſe Countries, where being in the midſt of oppoſitions, they put on greater appearances of Piety, Patience, Charity (as they call their Almſdeeds) and pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of greater Unity and Proſperity; and what was laſtly ſaid alſo of her wilineſs in accommodating her Doctrines, and carriages toward them, to mens different humors. But beſides theſe things there may be other cauſes that are more principal aſſigned, which in conjunction with theſe are of great power and influence; ſo as there is great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the fall of many into her embraces. As for inſtance,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mens own former, and hitherto Careleſneſs to acquaint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with, and ſeek to be eſtabliſhed in the truth, and to walk in it according to its Inſtructions, and that hath been, and is the caſe of too many both of our Gentry and of others of both Sexes, that though they have for many years had the Scriptures and Goſpel Doctrines among them, and many Learned and Solid diſocurſes publiſhed, to diſcover the deceits of the Romaniſts; yet they have not ſet their hearts toward God and Chriſt ſeriouſly, to know and walk in, and be obedient to his truth; but have reſted in a bare form of Godlineſs, denying the power of it, more minding the World and the things of it, their Eſtates, Riches, Honours, Pleaſures, Ornaments, Gallantry or Intemperancy, and what their corruptions lead them to, than how to ſerve and pleaſe God, and make ſuch right improvements of his truths, made known to and among them, as wherein they might be fitted for and accounted worthy of its utmoſt Benefits, eſpecially in theſe late and preſent days, in which, looſe and licentious principles and practiſes, of Atheiſm, infidelity and debauchery, take great place and have wonderfully in a few years thriven ſo as to overcome the Nations. Now God is marvailouſly jealous of his glory, and the glory of his Name and truth, and will not hold them guiltleſs that take or receive them in vain, that is, ſo as not to be made good by them, and therefore will puniſh them that ſo do, for this cauſe it was that he gave over the Gentiles to vile affections, and to groſs Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, becauſe, when he had in and by his works of creation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, made known himſelf to and among them, they did not glorify him as God, nor were thankful to him, but became vain in their Imaginations, and their Fooliſh Hearts were darkened, ſo as profeſſing themſelves to be wiſe, they became fools, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23, 24, 25. For this cauſe God alſo threatned us Chriſtians, that he would give way to the man of Sin to come in upon the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48544:35"/>
World with power, and ſigns, and lying wonders, after the manner of Sathan, and ſend ſtrong deluſions, that men might believe lyes and be Damned, even becauſe God had firſt ſent the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel among us, and men received not the love thereof, that they might be ſaved (namely from their Sins) nor believed it heartily, ſo as to obey it, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. Which horrible threatned judgment he hath ſadly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in the World, after the Chriſtian faith, being ſpread abroad in it, hath not been duly entertained, partly by leting looſe Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, and ſeting up a Kingdom in the World, as to its Eaſtern parts, that received and propagates his deluſions what they can, and partly by ſuffering <hi>Rome</hi> in theſe Weſtern parts, ſo to exalt her ſelf with all her corruptions and abominations, and ſurely this is one, and the main cauſe of the falling off of ſo many to her bad communion after ſuch detection of her ſo fully made, to which way hath alſo been the rather made by.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſad debauchings of the Nations, and filling them with Profaneneſs, uncleanneſs, &amp; irreligion, from the one end to the other thereof, which hath doubtleſs been the project, and work of ſome that hold the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and follow his pernicious ways, who taught <hi>Balak</hi> to caſt a ſtumbling block before the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to eat things ſacrificed to Idols, and to commit Fornication, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14. Or rather as <hi>Jezabel,</hi> that painted Strumpet, who ſeduced Gods People to commit fornication, (firſt) and (then) to eat things ſacrificed to Idols, firſt to commit Fornication, and then, as a fruit thereof to which they might that way be the eaſier drawn to eat things ſacrificed to Idols, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20. According to ſome Machivil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian principles, to make men firſt of no Religion, and then they may eaſily be drawn to embrace any falſe Religion; how much bodily Whoredom and Fornication overſpreads the Land, is too ſad as well as eaſy to obſerve, and ſurely its juſt with God when men give up themſelves to that, to give them over to Spiritual Fornication alſo, that they might fill up the meaſure of their Iniquities, and his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſeverer wrath might come upon them, and eſpecially, its the direct way to promote the Popiſh Religion and its ſpiritual Whoredoms, becauſe it gives ſuch indulgences to, and diſpenſations for the beloved Sins of bodily Fornication, promiſing to thoſe that practice ſuch Sins, Pardon and impunity (at leaſt after ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Purgatory Pains) for their Sins, and Heaven and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to at laſt, if they will but joyn themſelves in fellowſhip with that Church, and uphold its claims and Pretentions, though for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of a devouter complexion, as we have noted, ſhe can take ſome precious truths of God, compared in Scripture to Gold, yea, fine
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48544:35"/>
Gold, or to Silver ſeven times Purifyed in the fire, and his precious promiſes, which are as precious Pearls, more precious than Rubies, and mixing them with her own ſuperſtitions, make up pretty tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing medals, and formes or Images of devotion, and compoſures of Croizons, and religious exerciſes, to allure and bewitch them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yea, the familiarity and Friendſhip with Perſons of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or being yoked up with them, eſpecially in Marriage, proves a great inducement to diverſe to turn to them, for even ſuch corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencies and conjunctions with any falſe worſhipers have been allways pernicious, as may appear even in <hi>Solomon,</hi> who though a wiſe man, and of an exceeding large underſtanding, ſo as that (as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> obſerves) among many Nations, there was no King like him, who was beloved of God, yet even him did outlandiſh (or ſtrange) women (of a corrupt Religion) cauſe to Sin, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.26. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. For his Women inclined or turned away his Heart, ſo that it was not right with God, but he followed other Gods, and built high places for them, and who may preſume to ſtand under a temptation, when he voluntarily caſts himſelf into it, that <hi>Solomon</hi> could not ſtand upright under, though ſo wiſe a man? therefore God forbad <hi>Iſrael</hi> to joyn themſelves in affinity with Idolaters, by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying their Daughters, leaſt they ſhould prove a ſnare to them, and draw away their hearts after their Gods with them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.12, 13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.3, 4. But too many now adays for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get and willfully overlook ſuch warnings, not reguard ſuch threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, as that in <hi>Math.</hi> 2.11.12. Where after he had ſaid, <hi>Judah</hi> hath dealt treacherouſly, and an abomination is committed in <hi>Iſrael</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> for <hi>Iudah</hi> hath profaned the holyneſs of God, which he loved by Marrying the Daughter of a ſtrange God, he adds, the Lord will cut of the Man that doth this, the Maſter and the Scholer out of the Tabernacles of <hi>Judah,</hi> yea, the making friendſhips, and but contracting familiarities with Perſons of corrupt principles, or practiſes the Scripture notes and warns of as infectious and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; ſee to this purpoſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.20. and 22, 24, 25. and 23, 29, 20, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15. But ſuch warnings are in this caſe too much ſlighted.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To which we may add a particular ſubtlety &amp; craft of in the Romiſh Factors, in that to enſnare people, they raiſe and ſcatter reports among them, that great perſons in authority favour and underneath approve their Religion, Church and Doctrine, as knowing that the multitude too generally, and eſpecially the looſer ſort, and thoſe that are ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of honour, and of the favour of great Perſons, are apt to reſolve their Religion into the wills and pleaſures of Princes and great Perſons, and will be ready to comply with their judgments, and ſteer their courſe by what they take to be their Compaſs to any point, whither right or
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48544:36"/>
wrong; towards Hell or Heaven, as is to be ſeen in all Nations where the Religion of the Princes and their Courts bears the greateſt ſway a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their ſubjects; they being, as was ſaid before, the Gods that are by multitudes ſupreamly Worſhiped; or if it be mens own bellies, their caſe, honour, wealth, pleaſure, or the like, that is the higheſt and chief God with them; yet Kings, Princes, and great Perſons, they look at as the moſt powerful Mediators, by whoſe means or favour thoſe other things are moſt probably and fully to be compaſſed and enjoyed, and ſo their higheſt God may be moſt ſatisfyingly ſerved. That the Prieſts and Jeſuits take ſuch a courſe now adays to perſwade the people by ſuch an Argument, to comply with their Principles, we have it made publick in Print, by the confeſſion of the late converted Fryar, Mr. <hi>Anthony Aegan,</hi> in his Book wherein his Recantation Sermon Preached at <hi>London</hi> is Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where we meet with words to this effect, <q>That after his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Proteſtant Religion, ſeveral of the Papiſt Prieſts, and others living about <hi>Loughreats</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (whom, he ſaith, he is ready to name, and did thereby accuſe) did publickly report that his Majeſty, his Royal Highneſs, and all the Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> were privately of their Religion, uſing it as an argument to make or move him to fall back again to Popery.</q> See here what notorious falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods they fear not to report, to the ſcandal of Authority, yea, and of our Nation it ſelf, to carry on their own deſigns; for thanks be to God the contrary hereunto hath been, and is abundantly evidenced, as to ſuch a general overflowing of their Religion over all thoſe perſons whom they have ſo traduced. Surely, that cauſe is naught that the maintainers of ſtick not to manage by ſo vile and indirect Mediums, as ſo to bely and ſlander their Superiors; there is no queſtion but it is what they deſire &amp; would gladly effect, to make both the Kings Majeſty &amp; the Court, &amp; all the Nobility &amp; Gentry, of their mind &amp; Religion, but God forbid that ever they ſhould prevail upon them, or draw them, or any of them, into ſo great a miſchief, and ſo certain a way to their own everlaſting deſtruction. But no doubt but by ſuch ſuggeſtions they may prevail upon no ſmall party of men, whoſe Faith and Religion lies in the wills and practiſes of the Great ones, to liſten and conſent unto them, being too apt to take things upon truſt of their, (that is) theſe mens honeſty, and not duly weighing what is ſaid by them, and that queſtionleſs is one thing that proves an effectual Engine to draw away diſciples after them.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe and ſuch like accounts, this Church, though ſo corrupt, keeps up her ſelf yet in the world, and gets too much credit with too many, who are either not able, or not willing to ſearch into matters to find them out, with a diligent and impartial ſearch, with ſuch her Paints paſs for excellent beauty and comelineſs, eſpecially her pretty frames and forms of Devotion in her Prayers and Croiſons, partly to God and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48544:36"/>
Chriſt, and partly to Saints really or ſuppoſedly ſuch; Her abſtinences and penances, or other auſterities, which have ſuch a ſhew of excellency, (as the Apoſtle ſaith of the commandments of men, <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not: That they have a ſhew of wiſdom indeed, in will-worſhip and humility, and neglecting, or</hi> (as the Margin reads it) <hi>puniſhing, and not ſparing the body,</hi> Col. 2.21.23. As draws in unſtable Souls, and beguiles them, (as the Apoſtles phraſe is in verſ. 18.) of their reward, which things, divers of them, I mean Devotion, Abſtinence, Mortification, yea, and Almſdeeds, if rightly done, and upon right and ſound principles, are in themſelves very good, and may be, and are by ſome exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Proteſtant Principles, more worthily and acceptably than they can be upon thoſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in conjunction with their corruptions, by which all their beſts deeds are marred, though indeed I could wiſh they were more upon good and right principles, and in a good way practiſed among us, than they are, but it is too often found, that men are apter to do more in, and for a falſe way, than they or others are in and for a true, as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.8. <hi>The children of this world are in their generation wiſer than the children of light.</hi> So it may be ſaid alſo, that the worſhippers of Idols are more forward in their worſhip, than they that worſhip the true God, are in his worſhip; for ſo we find it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Idolaters, that they laviſh gold out of the bag, and weigh Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver out of the ballance, and ſpare for no coſt to make an Idol or falſe God, and then bear him upon their Shoulder, and carry him to his place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.6, 7. And as the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> notes, they deck it with Silver and Gold, and faſten it with nails; yea, Silver ſpread in Plates is brought from <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> and Gold from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>phaz;</hi> the work of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and of the hands of the Founder, blue and purple is their cloathing, <hi>&amp;c. Jer.</hi> 10.4.9. that is, they ſpare for neither coſt nor pains, nor mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how they burthen themſelves to carry on a falſe Religion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, when God, in and by Jeſus Chriſt, the former of all things, and our Redeemer, who proffers to carry and bear us, and work all our works for and in us, in our liſtning to him, and following his Word and Spirit, we are too prone to ſlight, and think much to put our ſelves to coſt and pains, and to ſtoop down to bear any burthens put upon us by him in and for his ſervice. <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the wilderneſs could readily pluck off their Jewels, and Ear-rings, to make themſelves a Molten Calf of, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.2, 3. when as afterward they could find in their hearts to put off God with the refuſe or worſt of what he gave them; yea, and to rob Him of his Tithes and Offerings, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.8.13. &amp; 3.8. and ſo the falſe Worſhippers of <hi>Rome</hi> are forwarder to put themſelves to faſtings and abſtinence after their faſhion, with Devotions, Alms-deeds, and the like, to make to themſelves a confidence of, or eſtabliſh to themſelves a righteouſneſs in, (as the Apoſtles Phraſe is in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3.) and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48544:37"/>
to themſelves thereby forgiveneſs of (that I ſay not with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to ſome of them, alſo a licenſe to practiſe) their Sins, and to merit and deſerve Gods favour and eternal Life: when we that have the purity and ſimplicity of the truth of God more clearly among us, and are Inſtructed into the alone ſufficiency in the grace in Chriſt Jeſus, and have all freely promiſed to us upon his account only in a way of obedience to him, and his inſtructions are yet too backward to yield up our ſelves to him, and to be at ſuch coſt and charge, and exerciſe ſuch pains and patience as his inſtructions direct us to, and his grace and love ingage us to, that we might enjoy the pourings out of his ſpirit upon us, glorify him worthily in our generations, and do good to others to our capacities.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Now upon all theſe premiſes I cannot but deſire for all men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for my friends and acquaintance, that the Lord would grant to them, that by all that is ſaid, or by what is otherwhere more fully and clearly ſaid by more learned Perſons, they may ſo diſcern, and ſee the Abominations of that Harlot, as to avoid them, and keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves far from them, not liſtening to any of their fair and ſpecious flatteries that would entice thereto, of whom I may ſay in <hi>Solomons</hi> words, <hi>None that go into her</hi> (that is, very few or none of thoſe that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly go into fellowſhip with her) <hi>return again, neither do they take hold of the paths of life,</hi> ſo as to walk in the way of good men, and keep the path of the righteous; but with the <hi>ſimple ones, and the young man void of underſtanding, that declining towards the corner of the ſtrange woman, go in the path to her houſe, who with her fair ſpeech are made to yeild, and with the flattering of her lips are inticed; they go after her, as the Ox to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or as a fool to the correction of the ſtocks, till a dart strike through their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as a Bird that haſteth to the ſnare, &amp; knows not that it is for their life,</hi> even for the life of their precious Souls. Oh! might what follows with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to this ſcarlet Whore be conſidered and received, wherein wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom adds—<hi>Hearken now therefore unto me, O ye Children, and attend to the words of my mouth. Let not thine heart decline or bend towards her way, go not astray in her paths; for ſhe hath caſt down many wounded; yea, many ſtrong men</hi> (men of ſtrong parts) <hi>have been ſlain by her,</hi> as to ſpiritual life. <hi>Her houſe is the way to Hell</hi> (whether men think and believe ſo or not) <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to the chambers of death,</hi> Prov. 2.19, 20. and 7.7, 8, 9.21.22.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For if the Scriptures be true, as undoubtedly they are (both they and we confeſs, that though they love to puzzle men with que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions needleſly, how they know them to be the Scriptures, or word of God, as if we muſt be beholding to them for that which is falſe) then ſeeing the Scriptures affirm that no Idolaters ſhall inherit the kingdom of God, nor any that love or make a lye, they then that are of, and hold communion with that Church, are in a ſad and piteous
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48544:37"/>
caſe, they being clearly guilty of Idolatry, and groſs falſhoods, as may from what is ſaid, &amp; many other things that I have omitted be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned. And though ſome men (they think) charitably ſuppoſe that ſome, who through their invincible Ignorance, are neceſſitated to live in their communion, may find mercy with God, they believing and holding the fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian faith, though joyned with ſuch corruptions, as they joyn therewith; whoſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable conceſſions to that purpoſe have, I fear, laid a ſnare for the feet of many; I am confident have been, and are abuſed to that purpoſe by her Prieſts and Jeſuits to draw many in to joyn with them (though no ground be given in them for that) and to hold in them that were before of it. Yet ſeeing (as I queſtion not) the falſe Apoſtles, and the <hi>Gallathians</hi> ſeduced by them, did hold the main Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith too, only joyned with them a neceſſity of Circumciſion, as theſe joyn a neceſſity of communion with their Church in all that ſhe injoynes and impoſeth, unto their ſalvation; and the Apoſtle for all that pronounced, that in caſe <hi>they were circumciſed, Chriſt would profit them nothing,</hi> Gall. 5.2. I know little ground we have for that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or what more than we may have for thoſe of the <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Pagans</hi> who are invincibly kept from the knowledge of the truth of God, and the true way of worſhipping him, received among us Chriſtians, by the prevalency of their falſe Teachers, or the ſeverities of their Rulers under whoſe power they live, that they alſo may be winked at of God and ſaved. Which if it may be ſuppoſed, yet affords no good ground for any of us Chriſtians to turn to any of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and as little have we from the forementioned charitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions or ſuppoſitions of ſome to turn to <hi>Romes</hi> communion. Nay, its moſt dreadfully dangerous for any that have known better, or been brought up under the Proteſtant profeſſion, where they have had or might have had clear convictions of the falſhoods and evils of that Church, to depart from righter ways to her deceits and corruptions. For to ſuch doubtleſs belongs that dreadful ſentence which we read of in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9, 10. among others unto whom its poſſible it may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after alſo be applicable upon a farther account. Where after the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels preaching the everlaſting Goſpel openly, as in the Mid-Heaven, and warning all Nations to fear God and worſhip him, in oppoſition to the falſe worſhip before in <hi>chap.</hi> 13. related; and another Angels proclaiming <hi>Babilon</hi> (that is <hi>Rome</hi>) to be fallen (both from the true Faith, and worſhip, and from her former luſtre, as before we explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it) there follows a third Angel proclaiming with a loud voice, that any man (namely, if now eſpecially after the two former proclamations either yet, or having not done ſo before now) <hi>ſhall worſhip the Beaſt, and his Image, and receive his Mark in his forehead, or in his hand,</hi> (ſhall either
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48544:38"/>
more openly or ſecretly, either in profeſſion or practice receive the mark and badge of communion and fellowſhip with the falſe worſhip of <hi>Rome,</hi> for that's clearly as was before noted, the Woman ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by, and riding the Beaſt, whoſe worſhippers are here threatned) <hi>the ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the wrath of God, which is without mixture poured into the Cup of his indignation, and ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb, and the ſmoke of their torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever; and they have no reſt day or night, who worſhip the Beaſt and his image, and whoſoever receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Mark of his name.</hi> A dreadful ſentence worthy to be thought of and trembled at by all that ſtill retain the falſe Idoatrous worſhip practiſed in the Romiſh Church, eſpecially by ſuch of them as live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Proteſtant reformed Churches, and more eſpecially ſtill that having had better light and education, do return or relapſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. A ſentence in which is no reſpect of perſons, but what or whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they be, high or low, rich or poor, Princes or peaſants, God will not be partial in his judgment upon them; but if they will venture upon theſe ſins, they muſt alſo expect to indure theſe terrible tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments here expreſſed, <hi>and the Mighty man ſhall cry there bitterly,</hi> Zeph. 1.14. O heavy portion of all our Engliſh Roman Catholicks. The Lord open their eyes to ſee the evil of the way they are in, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to renounce it, &amp; to depart therefrom, for it will be moſt ſad in the latter end. Though its probable that they of <hi>Rome</hi> may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe to make ſad the portion of ſuch as warn &amp; proteſt againſt them, &amp; deſire their converſion; and that they may alſo proſper a while in their deſigns, and bring ſad things upon the righter Worſhippers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their miſery come upon them, &amp; therefore it follows in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints, here are they that keep the Commandments of God, and the faith of Jeſus.</hi> Here namely about this time, when this is proclaimed; and this warning given that is mentioned in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going <hi>verſes,</hi> here is the patience of the Saints, then the Saints and right Worſhippers ſhall have a time to exerciſe their patience in wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the accompliſhment of that predicted judgment; or alſo they may have a ſad time of tryal, and therein for exerciſe of their pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence becauſe of ſome eminent ſufferings then befalling them, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them under which, and to keep the Commandments of God, and the faith of Jeſus, it is therefore added, <hi>That he heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying Writeb, leſſed are the dead that dy in the Lord, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works ſhall follow them,</hi> as implying that thenceforth would follow ſuch labours and ſufferings of the Saints, as well would it be with thoſe that ſhould endure them to death, ſo as to dy in the Lord; and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſhould be the dead of them rather than the living, before the ſad
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48544:38"/>
doom of the Beaſt-worſhippers come upon them. But yet as they that thenceforth eſpecially dy in the Lord ſhall be bleſſed, ſo the Beaſt-Worſhippers however long they may live, and their doom be deferred, are and ſhall be in the iſſue moſt accurſed.</p>
            <p>Which things being ſo, let us, I pray Sir, beware of that falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, keeping cloſe to the Scriptures of truth, and to the ſacred truths revealed in the Scriptures, and not for any reſpect, honour, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or worldly and carnal advantages reſpect them, and turn aſide to ſo corrupt and dangerous away and worſhip, as that of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Communion. God will certainly better bare with ſuch as have as it were been held captive by their deceits being always educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and brought up under them, then with ſuch as having been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſtructed, do turn aſide to them. Oh that theſe Nations and the Inhabitants thereof, would therefore look about them, and beware how they liſſen to any that would thereto ſeduce them, and mind thoſe many convincing arguments, and clear and unanſwerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of the deſperate badneſs of that Church, and its ways, and Doctrines, and doings, which by many hands have been offered to them, which yet if they pleaſe, they may conſult with and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, among which, beſide theſe many worthy men who have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly wrote excellently againſt her corruptions, as <hi>Jewel, Reinolds, Morton,</hi> and many others, the Labours of the Learned Doctor <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet,</hi> Dr. <hi>Tillitſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Brevint,</hi> Dr. <hi>Whitby,</hi> Sr. <hi>Chriſtopher Wyvel,</hi> (who it ſeems in his Minority was educated among or inſnared with them) and Mr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> in my judgment, are very worthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. And oh that men would not dally and trifle in ſo great a matter as their own Salvation, but be ſerious and conſiderative in what they do therein, allways remembring that of our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>What will it profit a man to gain the whole World, and looſe his own Soul? Or what ſhall a man give in Exchange for his Soul? For the Son of man ſhall come in the glory of his Father with his Angels, and then he will give to every man according to his Works, Math.</hi> 16.26.27. <hi>And that if thy hand offend thee, cut it off and caſt it from thee, and ſo if thy foot offend thee, for better it is to enter into the Kingdom of God, having but one hand or foot, and ſo halting or maimed, than having two hands or two feet to be caſt into Hell Fire, where the Worm dyeth not, and the fire is not quenched. And if thine Eye (thy right Eye) offend thee, pluck it out and caſt it from thee, for better it is to enter into the Kingdom of God having but one Eye, then having both thine Eyes to be caſt into Hell Fire where the Worms dyeth not, and the Fire is not quenched, Mark</hi> 9.44.48. Conſider what is herein (though but briefly and weakly) propounded, and the Lord bleſs it to every
one
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48544:39"/>
that may and ſhall read it, for the eſtabliſhing them in the truth where they are weak and wavering thereabout, if not, yet waved therefrom, and for the recovering ſuch as have declined or departed from it, and the Lord deliver us all from every evil work, and preſerve us to his everlaſting Kingdom, in whom I take my leave, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours and every Mans, to ſerve you and them in the faith and truth of Chriſt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
